<?xml version="1.0"?>
<learningObject editorVersion="3" targetFolder="Nottingham" name="Protecting sensitive data" language="en-GB" navigation="Linear" textSize="12" theme="default" displayMode="fill window" responsive="true"><bullets linkID="PG1581343208066" name="Learning objectives" delaySecs="1" showBullets="0" showPanel="0" panelWidth="Full"><![CDATA[<p>This unit introduces you to legal and ethical considerations for researchers working with sensitive data.</p>
<br />
<p>After completing this unit you will understand:
</p>
  <br />
<p>
  ▪ what sensitive data are
</p>
<p>▪ what data protection laws are and how they apply to research data
</p>
<p>▪ what types of research will be subject to ethical review
</p>
<p>▪ what consent documentation is appropriate to ensure you meet your ethical and legal obligations
</p>
<p>▪ the key aspects of data management needed to safeguard sensitive data
</p>
<p>▪ where to find appropriate data protection training
</p>
]]></bullets><textGraphics linkID="PG1594997483434" name="Introduction" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/ethics-2991600_960_720_(1).jpg'" tip="Right and wrong turn sign image by Tumisu (pixabay, No attribution required)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>When conducting research there are a number of ethical and legal considerations which may affect how your research data are collected, managed and shared.</p>

<p>Understanding your obligations as a researcher will enable you to adopt appropriate data protection-compliant strategies and help you to follow good practice in research integrity and research data management.</p>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1580136721813" name="What makes data sensitive?" textWidth="760"><![CDATA[<p>We use <strong>sensitive data</strong>&nbsp;as a catch-all term to refer to:</p>

<ul>
	<li>research data containing information which can be used to identify a human data subject;</li>
	<li>confidential data, including data generated or used under a restrictive commercial research funding agreement;</li>
	<li>ecological data, where the release of data may adversely affect rare or endangered&nbsp;species of plants or animals;</li>
	<li>data likely to harm an individual or community, or have a significant negative public impact, if released.</li>
</ul>

<p>Other kinds of research data may also be considered sensitive, and researchers should therefore use their own judgement to determine whether research data should be considered as sensitive.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1580312237991" name="UK and European data protection laws" textWidth="760"><![CDATA[<p>The Data Protection Act 2018 is the UK&#39;s implementation of the&nbsp;General Data Protection Regulation (commonly known as&nbsp;GDPR) and applies to the <strong>processing </strong>of <strong>personal data</strong></p>

<ul>
	<li>about people residing inside and&nbsp;outside the European Economic Area (EEA), by people within&nbsp;the EEA</li>
	<li>about people inside the EEA, by people outside the EEA</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Personal data</strong> is&nbsp;information about <strong>identifiable living people&nbsp;</strong>who can be&nbsp;identified using the data, either directly or indirectly.</p>

<p><strong>Processing </strong>means doing anything with a person&#39;s information, including collection, storage, analysis, sharing, deletion, and destruction.</p>

<p>For research, this&nbsp;means that research data containing&nbsp;<strong>direct identifiers&nbsp;</strong>(e.g. a person&#39;s name, address, or other unique identifier&nbsp;such as their NHS or Social Security number) will be subject to data protection laws.</p>

<p>Even if research data contain no direct identifiers,&nbsp;an individual may still be identifiable using a combination of <strong>indirect identifiers</strong> (e.g. health, economic, cultural or social characteristics) and so data protection laws will therefore still apply.</p>

<p>There are additional requirements when handling <strong>&#39;special category data&#39;</strong> relating to a person&#39;s racial/ethnic origin, political opinions, religious/philosophical beliefs, trade union membership, genetic and biometric data, physical or mental health, sex life, and sexual orientation.</p>

<ul>
</ul>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1630679029222" name="UK GDPR after leaving the EU"><![CDATA[<ul>
	<li>The General Data Protection Regulation has been kept in UK law as the UK GDPR.</li>
</ul>

<ul>
	<li>In June 2021 the EU Commission approved adequacy decisions&nbsp;for the EU GDPR and the Law Enforcement Directive (LED)&nbsp;meaning data can continue to flow between the UK and the EU&nbsp;as it did before in the majority of circumstances.</li>
</ul>

<ul>
	<li>This means data protection laws continue&nbsp;to apply to the processing of personal data in the UK.</li>
</ul>

<ul>
</ul>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1594997616177" name="What do&amp;nbsp;data protection laws&amp;nbsp;mean&amp;nbsp;for my research?" align="Right" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/GDPR_principles_3.PNG'" tip="GDPR Data Protection Principles image by MANTRA team (CC-BY 4.0)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>According to GDPR, anyone working with <strong>personal data</strong>&nbsp;must follow <strong>six key data protection principles</strong> (shown in the image on the left) which are designed to&nbsp;ensure that people&#39;s data are&nbsp;handled with due care and attention. Additionally, you are required to&nbsp;maintain an audit trail and&nbsp;be able to demonstrate your compliance with these principles.</p>

<p>To understand how data protection laws apply to you and your research data, you should consult your own institution&#39;s guidance on data protection and GDPR.</p>

<p>You can find an example of data protection guidance for researchers from the University of Edinburgh from the University&rsquo;s data protection officer below:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/records-management/guidance/research/data-protection" target="_blank">Data protection for research (University of Edinburgh, Records Management section)</a></p>

<p>For&nbsp;research data relating&nbsp;to people outside the EEA&nbsp;you must also ensure you are aware of and comply with applicable data protection laws in the respective region. For example, the&nbsp;Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) in the US.</p>
]]></textGraphics><quiz linkID="PG1580314712895" name="ACTIVITY: GDPR quiz" order="sequence" numQuestions="*" align="left" panelWidth="Full" instructions="&lt;p&gt;Now you have an understanding of data protection laws, see if you can identify the contexts in which GDPR applies to research.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Press &amp;#39;Submit&amp;#39; for feedback on your answers.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" judge="false" showfeedback="true" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Well done! Please click the right arrow&amp;nbsp;button below to continue with the unit.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" quesCount="Question {i} of {n}" feedbackLabel="Feedback" singleRight="Your answer is correct!" singleWrong="Your answer is incorrect" multiRight="You have selected all the correct answers" multiWrong="You have not selected the correct combination of answers" onCompletion="You have completed the exercise" score="You scored {i} / {n}" submitBtnText="Submit" nextBtnText="Next" restartBtnText="Restart"><question linkID="PG1587124946091" prompt="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which of the following statements is correct? &lt;/strong&gt;Please select all answers that apply.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GDPR legislation applies&amp;nbsp;to research...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Question" type="Multiple Answer" answerOrder="sequence"><option linkID="PG1587125542513" text="&lt;p&gt;conducted&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;inside the EEA&lt;/strong&gt;, involving processing personal data about subjects outside the EEA&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes, if you&amp;nbsp;are in the EEA&amp;nbsp;and you are processing personal data then GDPR legislation will apply, whether or not your data subjects are inside the EEA.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additionally, the implementation of the UK Data Protection Act 2018 means that GDPR requirements will continue to apply to the processing of personal data in the UK once the UK leaves the EU. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="true"/><option linkID="PG1587125318602" text="&lt;p&gt;conducted&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;outside the EEA&lt;/strong&gt;, involving processing personal data about subjects within the EEA&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes, if you process personal data about people within the EEA&amp;nbsp;then GDPR will apply, whether or not you are inside the EEA.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="true"/><option linkID="PG1587126059104" text="&lt;p&gt;conducted&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;outside the EEA&lt;/strong&gt;, which &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; involve processing personal data about subjects within the EEA&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No, GDPR does not apply in this case as neither the data controller nor the data subjects are within the EEA. For research conducted in other non-EEA regions, you should ensure that you comply with data protection legislation applicable in the respective region.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/></question></quiz><text linkID="PG1580140242336" name="Research ethics" textWidth="760"><![CDATA[<p>In addition to any legal obligations, research involving <strong>human participants</strong>, <strong>human material</strong>, <strong>personal data</strong> or <strong>live animals</strong> will normally be subject to ethical review to ensure the proposed study is conducted ethically.</p>

<p>Ethical principles are in line with or extend beyond legal principles, and cover:</p>

<ul>
	<li>the purpose and nature of the research itself</li>
	<li>how consent is communicated and recorded</li>
	<li>what data need to be safeguarded during analysis, and destroyed after use</li>
</ul>

<p>The University of Edinburgh subscribes to the UK Research Integrity Office&#39;s Research Code of Practice. In addition, your college and school are likely to have their own research ethics committees or procedures.</p>

<p>For those outside the UK, be aware of the applicable ethical review procedures within your own institution and research area. For example, institutional review boards play the role of ethics committees in the US.</p>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1594997730881" name="Informed consent" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/consent-2052052_960_720.jpg'" tip="Consent checkbox and pen image by Catkin (pixabay, No attribution required)." transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Informed, voluntary and fair consent to participate in a study is the cornerstone of ethical research involving people. It is intended to ensure that the rights of individual participants are respected and is closely linked with the participant information sheet.</p>

<p>It is through this ethics consent process that research participants can understand what taking part in a specific study will mean for them. Each person can then choose whether to participate using the consent form.</p>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1627392081932" name="Video: capturing consent"><![CDATA[<p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M0tRSQx-cfQ" title="YouTube video player" width="560"></iframe></p>

<p>Professor Lynn Jamieson, Centre for Research on Families and Relationships, University of Edinburgh, talks about gaining informed consent from research subjects and how written consent may not be possible in the context of certain types of social research.</p>

<p>Playback quality and subtitles may be adjusted using the options menu (click&nbsp;the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch this&nbsp;video directly on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M0tRSQx-cfQ&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GMGCrHWwCYgW5Nnm_xwpvmP&amp;index=5" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p>

<p>A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1580141524235" name="Video transcript" textWidth="760"><![CDATA[<p>Consent forms I think are quite a tricky issue. I do use a consent form, but I didn&#39;t when I started. At that time it wasn&#39;t yet a standard procedure. There might still be some circumstances in which I wouldn&#39;t use a consent form. If you are doing some sorts of participant observation work, there are lots of people coming and going, you can&#39;t realistically use a consent form. Also, some people find a consent form really intimidating - it&#39;s very off-putting.<br />
<br />
I would always give people a written description and a verbal description and I would get their permission verbally, and I would ask them to sign a consent form usually. But that consent form, if you want to archive the data, has to explain that it&#39;s going to be archived, and how it (maybe) could then be used. But not everybody knows what an archive is, and so it&#39;s really important to try and use very clear language about these things, that&#39;s... (you know) that is an honest description but isn&#39;t an unnecessarily off-putting description, that doesn&#39;t make it sound like you&#39;re going to become, you know, an object that everybody&#39;s pointing to in some way.</p>
]]></text><tabNav linkID="PG1580140864765" name="Consent documentation" text="&lt;p&gt;In order that research participants&amp;#39; consent is informed, voluntary, and fair, your consent documentation should include:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;participant information sheet&lt;/strong&gt; and&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;consent form&lt;/strong&gt; signed by the participant&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;b&gt;tabs on the right&lt;/b&gt; provide further information about what participant information sheets and consent forms should include.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Medium"><nestedPage linkID="PG1580140908634" name="&lt;strong&gt;Participant information sheet&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;participant information sheet&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;is used to inform prospective participants about the study. The&amp;nbsp;information should be written in clear and easy to understand language and should cover the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;What the project is about&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;What their participation will involve&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Any risks involved for participants and&amp;nbsp;safeguards to minimise those risks&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Assurances about data security and participant confidentiality&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;How data will be used in&amp;nbsp;the study (e.g. tables of aggregated data for published articles, reports and presentations)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Proposed plans for archiving data at the end of the study and potential future secondary re-use of data&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Details of the organisation overseeing the research&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Who to contact for more information about the study&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1580141332689" name="&lt;strong&gt;Consent form&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;consent form&lt;/strong&gt; is used to verify that the research participant understands&amp;nbsp;and agrees to participate in the study.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The consent form should cover the following points (but not limited to):&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;The participant has read and understood the participant information sheet.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;The participant has been given the opportunity to ask questions.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;The participant understands that participation is voluntarily.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;The participant understands that they may withdraw from the study at any time without giving reasons and without penalty (where applicable).&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;The participant understands how the data will be managed, shared and archived (as detailed in the information sheet).&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Signature&amp;nbsp;and date&amp;nbsp;of signing for the participant and the researcher.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/></tabNav><textGraphics linkID="PG1594997813633" name="Privacy by design" align="Right" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/data_protection_by_default_BS.jpg'" tip="Privacy by design image by MANTRA team (CC-BY 4.0), incorporates 'Smartphone security' image by BiljaST (Pixabay, No attribution required)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Data protection law&nbsp;requires you to adopt a &lsquo;data protection by design and default&rsquo; approach.</p>

<p>This means that when planning a research project, you should be thinking about how you will secure your research data and protect the privacy of your research subjects&nbsp;from beginning to&nbsp;end.</p>

<p>For example, think ahead and plan how you will:</p>

<ul>
	<li>collect and store the data</li>
	<li>manage files and copies</li>
	<li>control access permissions</li>
	<li>prepare data&nbsp;for archiving/sharing at the end of the project</li>
</ul>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1580142279071" name="Data protection impact assessment" textWidth="760"><![CDATA[<p>For research involving personal or sensitive data it is recommended for you to complete a <strong>data protection impact assessment</strong> (DPIA).</p>

<p>Conducting a <strong>DPIA </strong>will help you to</p>

<ul>
	<li>Ensure compliance with applicable legal, regulatory, and policy requirements for privacy;</li>
	<li>Determine the risks and effects; and</li>
	<li>Evaluate protections and alternative processes to mitigate potential privacy risks.</li>
</ul>

<p>Your own institution can provide guidance on conducting a DPIA for your research project. For example, see the following link for University of Edinburgh guidance on DPIAs (including a template and guidance for students under the &#39;Student Research&#39; section):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/records-management/guidance/checklist/data-protection-impact-assessment" target="_blank">Data protection impact assessment (DPIA) (University of Edinburgh, Records Management section)</a></p>

<p>A DPIA should be considered in addition to writing a data management plan (DMP) at the beginning of the project (see the MANTRA &#39;Data Management Plans&#39; module for more information). A DMP will help you to plan ahead and think through how you will manage your data throughout your project.</p>
]]></text><tabNav linkID="PG1587142061458" name="Approvals processes" text="&lt;p&gt;If your research project will involve accessing potentially identifiable data from a third party source (e.g. NHS patient data or other administrative data, or data shared under a restrictive license or data sharing agreement) you should ensure you are aware of the relevant application and approvals process.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Medium"><nestedPage linkID="PG1587142111190" name="Approvals process" text="&lt;p&gt;The exact process for gaining approvals (and the documentation that is needed) will vary according to who controls the data and what type of data is being requested.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Before submitting an application, be sure to read available guidance and documentation about the application process. Be aware that the approvals process can be lengthy and it may take many months (or even years) for access to be&amp;nbsp;granted. As such, you should ensure you factor in the time taken to&amp;nbsp;receive relevant approvals when planning your project.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Access to restricted third party data, such as NHS data or administrative data from other sources, is reliant on approvals from the designated regulatory or governance body. For example, applications to use NHS data for research in England and Wales are reviewed by&amp;nbsp;the Health Research Authority (HRA) (see &amp;lsquo;Further reading&amp;rsquo; for more information on HRA approvals).&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For non-UK restricted data access you should consult the relevant approvals body to check the requirements and approvals needed. In the US for example, access to restricted health data from the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) requires submission of a proposal to the Research Data Center.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/><nestedPage linkID="PG1587142088919" name="Application to access restricted data" text="&lt;p&gt;An application to access restricted data will commonly involve submission of a detailed research proposal. The following list outlines the key points that a proposal should normally cover:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;the research question(s) being explored&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;a list of the specific data and variables needed to answer the research question(s), including&amp;nbsp;justification for using potentially disclosive data, rather than using less sensitive data sources&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;definition of roles detailing who will access the data and why&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;proposed methods for ensuring confidentiality of the data, including: security of physical environment; security of the data and associated files (e.g. encryption, access controls, data retention plan, method for secure deletion)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;any planned sharing of data and publication of results, including how data and results will be anonymised&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;details of relevant data protection training taken by all individuals who will have access to the data (certified training may be a necessary requirement for access to particularly sensitive data)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;" align="Top"/></tabNav><nav linkID="PG1580316930919" name="Safeguarding sensitive data" text="&lt;p&gt;When working with data about people, data protection laws require you to apply appropriate &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;technological and organisational measures&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot; to ensure personal data is handled appropriately and securely. There are a number of strategies that you can adopt to safeguard the privacy of your research subjects, and these include:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Data minimisation&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Data retention limits&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Secure data transfer&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Encryption&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Access controls&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Anonymisation&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Press each button to see more information about each topic.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Button" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1580316961129" name="Data minimisation" text="&lt;p&gt;Data minimisation is a key principle in data protection law, relating to the amount of identifying information that you collect and hold about people.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;In practice this means you shouldn&amp;#39;t collect or keep identifying information longer than is necessary.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Think of the following:&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;  &lt;li&gt;if personal information isn&amp;#39;t needed, don&amp;#39;t collect it&lt;/li&gt;&#10;  &lt;li&gt;if it is needed, keep it securely&lt;/li&gt;&#10;  &lt;li&gt;periodically review whether you are retaining unnecessary identifying information&lt;/li&gt;&#10;  &lt;li&gt;when identifying information is no longer needed, safely remove, delete or destroy it&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1580317247033" name="Data retention limits" text="&lt;p&gt;Deciding how long you will retain identifiable data before removing direct identifiers, applying more complex anonymisation techniques, or deleting the data altogether will help you to comply with data protection laws.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Data retention limits are common practice when working with restricted data from third parties. Access to data shared under a specific license or data sharing agreement commonly requires data to be securely deleted following an agreed period for conducting the research.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;When considering the deletion of sensitive data you need to be aware that standard methods for deleting files (e.g.&amp;nbsp;moving files to the recycle bin and emptying it) are not secure, as deleted files may be recovered.&amp;nbsp;It may be necessary to conduct a risk assessment on the data, including assessment of the type of storage used, to determine the most appropriate method for deleting or destroying sensitive data securely.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;You should also plan the retention of original collection instruments, such as paper questionnaires or interview recordings. Once these are transferred into an analysis package or a transcript and quality assured or validated, there may no longer be a reason to retain them.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Questions of which data to keep and for how long need to be considered in the context of your ability to maintain the confidentiality of your subjects&amp;#39; information, and should be planned in advance.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1580917761551" name="Secure data transfer" text="&lt;p&gt;Data protection laws place restrictions on the transfer of personal data, and personal data should not be transferred outside of the EEA. The UK&amp;rsquo;s Information Commissioners Office (ICO) provides detailed guidance on data transfer restrictions, including outlining conditions under which personal data may be transferred:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-data-protection/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/international-transfers/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International transfers under GDPR (ICO)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Before considering the transfer of personal data, you should think through whether the transfer of identifiable data is necessary. For example, can data be de-identified or anonymised? If data cannot be made unidentifiable then you must ensure you have authority to transfer the personal data, and that there are appropriate safeguards in place to protect the data before, during and after transit.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;You should make sure that any system you choose for the transfer of sensitive data is secure. Where possible, it is recommended to use contracted services which can certify they are GDPR compliant. Widely available services (e.g. Dropbox, Google Drive, etc) provide no user control over where or how data will be processed, and use of such services is therefore not recommended without an organisational contract.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1580317124329" name="Encryption" text="&lt;p&gt;Encryption provides protection by ensuring that only someone with the relevant encryption key (password) will be able to access the contents.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Encrypting sensitive data will ensure that it cannot be accessed by non-authorised people. Encryption allows you to secure sensitive data by:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;encrypting a single file&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;creating an encrypted container (i.e. a folder) on a hard drive&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;encrypting a computer / laptop&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;encrypting other devices (e.g. smartphones, tablets)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Note, encrypting a single file is not recommended. Rather, it is advised to create an encrypted container and store sensitive files securely inside it.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1580317376632" name="Access controls" text="&lt;p&gt;You should consider applying access controls to ensure that only authorised individuals are able to access sensitive data. For example, standard access control methods include the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;password protection&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;management of shared folder permissions&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For those working with particularly sensitive data, &lt;strong&gt;data safe havens&lt;/strong&gt; and other dedicated secure or safe settings employ strict protocols and controls to ensure the integrity and security of the data within the environment. Such services ensure the security of data by placing restrictions on the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Who can access the data &amp;ndash; only approved researchers&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Where data can be accessed &amp;ndash; a specific physical location, a designated PC&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;What can be done with the data &amp;ndash; access to a limited set of tools/software/processes&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;What can be removed from the environment &amp;ndash; application of disclosure control to secondary outputs such as&amp;nbsp;tables of results&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;If your data are sensitive you should check whether standard access controls are sufficient to secure the data. Access to restricted third party data may be dependent on use of a particular safe settings environment or service. Alternatively, your own institution may provide a secure data environment or service.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1580317550848" name="Anonymisation" text="&lt;p&gt;Anonymization is a process by which identifying information in a dataset is removed or masked, and is used primarily to enable data to be shared or published without revealing the confidential information it contains, while limiting the loss of information.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Where possible, &lt;strong&gt;direct identifiers&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. names, addresses, telephone numbers, account numbers, etc.) should be removed as soon as the identifying information is no longer needed, by deleting them or replacing them with pseudonyms. For qualitative data, replace or generalise identifying characteristics when transcribing interviews.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;De-identified data that can be re-identified using a linkage file (i.e. information linking data subjects to identifiable individuals) is known as pseudonymised data. &lt;strong&gt;NOTE: In this instance, the linkage file should be encrypted and stored securely and separately from the de-identified research data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Identification of individuals in pseudonymised or de-identified data&amp;nbsp;may still be possible using combinations of &lt;strong&gt;indirect identifiers&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. age, education, employment, geographic area, medical conditions, etc). Further, data and outputs (e.g. tables of results) containing small cell counts may be potentially disclosive, particularly where samples are drawn from small populations or include cases with extreme values or relatively rare characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;As such, when intending to share potentially identifiable data or the outputs generated from the data, you may need to consider more advanced anonymisation techniques such as statistical disclosure control (SDC). You can find information and guidance about SDC, in &amp;lsquo;Further reading&amp;rsquo; at the end of this unit.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nav><quiz linkID="PG1587140130079" name="ACTIVITY: Direct or indirect identifier?" order="random" numQuestions="*" align="left" panelWidth="Medium" instructions="&lt;p&gt;Consider the following identifiers and decide which of these are direct identifiers (please select all that apply)?&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" judge="false" showfeedback="true" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Although indirect identifiers cannot uniquely identify an individual, in combination they increase the risk of re-identification. The risk of re-identification is greater for data subjects with&amp;nbsp;uncommon characteristics or with extreme values on a given measure, particularly in the context of smaller populations (e.g. small geographic areas).&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" quesCount="Question {i} of {n}" feedbackLabel="Feedback" singleRight="Your answer is correct!" singleWrong="Your answer is incorrect" multiRight="You have selected all the correct answers" multiWrong="You have not selected the correct combination of answers" onCompletion="You have completed the exercise" score="You scored {i} / {n}" submitBtnText="Submit" nextBtnText="Next" restartBtnText="Restart"><question linkID="PG1587140366651" prompt="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which of the following are direct identifiers? &lt;/strong&gt;Please select all that apply.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Question" type="Multiple Answer" answerOrder="random"><option linkID="PG1587140403194" text="&lt;p&gt;name&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes, a person&amp;#39;s name is a direct identifier as it can be used to directly identify an individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="true"/><option linkID="PG1587140423634" text="&lt;p&gt;personal address&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes, a personal address is a direct identifier as it can be used to directly&amp;nbsp;identify a household and/or an individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="true"/><option linkID="PG1587140449082" text="&lt;p&gt;NHS or social security number&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes, NHS or social security NHS or social security numbers are direct identifiers as they are unique so can be used to directly identify an individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="true"/><option linkID="PG1587140477974" text="&lt;p&gt;medical condition&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No, a medical condition is an indirect identifier as it cannot be used alone to directly identify an individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option linkID="PG1587140511217" text="&lt;p&gt;job title&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No, a person&amp;#39;s job is an indirect identifier as it cannot be used alone to uniquely identify an individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option linkID="PG1587140533274" text="&lt;p&gt;ethnic origin&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No, a person&amp;#39;s ethnic origin is an indirect identifier as it cannot be used alone to uniquely identify an individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/></question></quiz><youtube linkID="PG1588775216717" name="Making data available to others" text="&lt;p&gt;In terms of data sharing, there is currently a tension between the risks of personal disclosure and the pressure to make data openly available as part of the record of research.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;If you plan to share or publish your data you must ensure that your data are appropriate and safe to share. For example, you should consider whether the data can be adequately anonymised, and whether anonymised data will remain useful.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;After applying methods to de-identify and anonymise sensitive data, there may still be a risk of re-identification. You should then consider applying access controls to ensure the data are shared appropriately and securely. This may involve finding a data repository which can provide suitable access controls.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This video by the University of Bristol talks about the issues surrounding sharing sensitive research data, including methods to secure potentially identifiable data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gFNznhqrpIs" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1580917718402" name="Data sharing agreements"><![CDATA[<p>When sensitive data need to be shared, for example between one organisation and another organisation or third party, a data sharing agreement may be&nbsp;used to specify the conditions under which the data are to be used.</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;[A data sharing agreement] sets out the purpose of the data sharing, covers what is to happen to the data at each stage, sets standards and helps all the parties to be clear about their respective roles. It helps you to demonstrate your accountability under the GDPR.&rdquo;</em><br />
ICO Data sharing code of practice</p>

<p>For more information about data sharing agreements, see the ICO &quot;Data sharing code of practice&quot;&nbsp;linked in &lsquo;Further reading&rsquo; at the end of this unit.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1588768721563" name="Training"><![CDATA[<p>Undertaking data protection training can provide the guidance and information you need to help you to work with sensitive and personal data ethically, legally and safely.</p>

<p>In particular, when working with sensitive third party data you may be required to provide proof that you have completed a certified data protection training course.</p>

<p>There are a number of online courses available which provide introductory and more advanced training about data protection laws, data security, and other aspects of working with sensitive data.</p>

<p>Examples of online data protection training courses include (links open in new window or tab):</p>

<ul>
	<li><strong>FOSTER Open Science </strong><a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/learning/data-protection-and-ethics/" target="_blank">Data protection and ethics</a></li>
	<li><strong>ICPSR </strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9vdWseLay9g&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;list=PLqC9lrhW1VvaKgzk-S87WwrlSMHliHQo6" target="_blank">Disclosure Risk Training -- For Public-Use or Not for Public Use, That Is the Question (video)</a></li>
	<li><strong>Medical Research Council </strong><a href="https://byglearning.co.uk/mrcrsc-lms/course/index.php?categoryid=1" target="_blank">Research, GDPR and confidentiality &ndash; what you really need to know</a>&nbsp;[requires registration]</li>
	<li><strong>University of Bristol </strong><a href="https://data.blogs.bristol.ac.uk/bootcampSD/" target="_blank">Sensitive research data bootcamp</a></li>
</ul>

<p>In addition,&nbsp;library research support services should&nbsp;be able to advise you on the availability of data protection training at your own institution.</p>
]]></text><gapFill linkID="PG1588758758939" name="Summary (1 of 3): Data protection laws" text="&lt;p&gt;You have now completed the &amp;lsquo;Protecting sensitive data&amp;rsquo; unit. As a summary task please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the gaps left in the text.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hint&lt;/strong&gt;: If the word you select is not the correct word you won&amp;#39;t be able to drop it into the gap.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" passage="&lt;p&gt;The General Data Protection Regulation&amp;nbsp;applies to the |processing| of personal data. Personal data is&amp;nbsp;information about |identifiable| living people&amp;nbsp;who can be identified&amp;nbsp;using the data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;An individual may potentially be identifiable from the data either&amp;nbsp;directly, for example by&amp;nbsp;a |name|&amp;nbsp;or social security&amp;nbsp;number, or indirectly, for example&amp;nbsp;by a combination of attributes such as |health|,&amp;nbsp;social or cultural characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Well done. Please continue to the second part of the activity on the next screen.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Medium" checkBtn="Check" showBtn="Show Answers" gapFillWrong="You have not filled in any answers correctly. Please try again." gapFillWrongTracking="You have not filled in any answers correctly." gapFillIncomplete="Please complete the exercise." gapFillPartWrongTracking="Your correct answers are shown in green." gapFillPartWrong="Your correct answers are shown in green. Try again with those you have got wrong."/><gapFill linkID="PG1588774017742" name="Summary (2 of 3): Consent" text="&lt;p&gt;Please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the gaps left in the text.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hint&lt;/strong&gt;: If the word you select is not the correct word you won&amp;#39;t be able to drop it into the gap.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" passage="&lt;p&gt;Consent documentation should include a participant |information| sheet and a consent form signed by the participant.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The consent form is used to verify that the research participant |understands| and agrees to |participate| in the study.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Well done. Please continue to the third part of the activity on the next screen&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Medium" checkBtn="Check" showBtn="Show Answers" gapFillWrong="You have not filled in any answers correctly. Please try again." gapFillWrongTracking="You have not filled in any answers correctly." gapFillIncomplete="Please complete the exercise." gapFillPartWrongTracking="Your correct answers are shown in green." gapFillPartWrong="Your correct answers are shown in green. Try again with those you have got wrong."/><gapFill linkID="PG1588775090802" name="Summary (3 of 3): Safeguarding data" text="&lt;p&gt;Please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the gaps left in the text.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hint&lt;/strong&gt;: If the word you select is not the correct word you won&amp;#39;t be able to drop it into the gap.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" passage="&lt;p&gt;Strategies that you can adopt to safeguard the privacy of your research subjects include:&amp;nbsp;data |minimisation|;&amp;nbsp;data retention limits;&amp;nbsp;secure data transfer;&amp;nbsp;|encryption|;&amp;nbsp;access controls;&amp;nbsp;anonymisation.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;De-identified data that can be re-identified using a linkage file is known as |pseudonymised| data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Data |safe| havens&amp;nbsp;employ strict protocols and controls to ensure the integrity and security of the data within the environment.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Well done, that&amp;#39;s it!&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Medium" checkBtn="Check" showBtn="Show Answers" gapFillWrong="You have not filled in any answers correctly. Please try again." gapFillWrongTracking="You have not filled in any answers correctly." gapFillIncomplete="Please complete the exercise." gapFillPartWrongTracking="Your correct answers are shown in green." gapFillPartWrong="Your correct answers are shown in green. Try again with those you have got wrong."/><text linkID="PG1580922363438" name="Next &amp;amp; further reading"><![CDATA[<p><b>What to do next?</b>
  <br />
  <br />
  You have now completed this unit. Take a look at the &#39;Further reading&#39; where you will find a list of resources that will help you gain further understanding of the topics covered in this unit.
  <br />
  <br />
  You could also start a new unit and come back to check these resources later. We recommend that you continue with the <a href="../fairsharingandaccess/">FAIR sharing and access</a> unit.
  <br />
  <br />
  If you prefer, you can also go back to the <a href="http://mantra.ed.ac.uk/">MANTRA</a> home page and choose a different unit.
  <br />
  &nbsp;
</p>
<p><b>Further reading</b>
</p>
<p>&nbsp;
</p>
<p>Association of Internet Researchers (2019). <em>Internet Research: Ethical Guidelines 3.0.</em>
  <br />
  <a href="https://aoir.org/reports/ethics3.pdf" target="_blank">https://aoir.org/reports/ethics3.pdf</a>
</p>
<p>DataSpan. (2018). <em>What Are the Different Types of Data Destruction and Which One Should You Use?</em>
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.dataspan.com/blog/what-are-the-different-types-of-data-destruction-and-which-one-should-you-use/" target="_blank">https://www.dataspan.com/blog/what-are-the-different-types-of-data-destruction-and-which-one-should-you-use/</a>
</p>
<p>Desai, T., Ritchie, F., &amp; Welpton, R. (2016). <em>Five Safes: Designing data access for research.</em> University of the West of England.
  <br />
  <a href="https://uwe-repository.worktribe.com/output/914745" target="_blank">https://uwe-repository.worktribe.com/output/914745</a>
</p>
<p>Information Commissioner&#39;s Office (ICO). <em>Guide to the General Data Protection Regulation.&nbsp;</em>Retrieved 11 April 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/" target="_blank">https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/</a>
</p>
<p>ICO. (2019). <em>Data sharing code of practice</em> (PDF).
  <br />
  <a href="https://ico.org.uk/media/2615361/data-sharing-code-for-public-consultation.pdf" target="_blank">https://ico.org.uk/media/2615361/data-sharing-code-for-public-consultation.pdf</a>
</p>
<p>Information Security Section, University of Edinburgh. <em>Encrypting devices and documents.</em> Retrieved 12 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/infosec/how-to-protect/encrypting" target="_blank">https://www.ed.ac.uk/infosec/how-to-protect/encrypting</a>
</p>
<p>Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR). <em>Recommended Informed Consent Language for Data Sharing.</em> Retrieved 15 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/pages/datamanagement/confidentiality/conf-language.html" target="_blank">https://www.icpsr.umich.edu/web/pages/datamanagement/confidentiality/conf-language.html</a>
</p>
<p>Keerie, C., Tuck, C., Milne, G. et al. (2018). <em>Data sharing in clinical trials &ndash; practical guidance on anonymising trial datasets.</em> Trials 19, 25.
  <br />
  <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13063-017-2382-9" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1186/s13063-017-2382-9</a>
</p>
<p>National Cyber Security Centre. (2016). <em>Secure sanitisation of storage media.</em>
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/secure-sanitisation-storage-media" target="_blank">https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/secure-sanitisation-storage-media</a>
</p>
<p>NHS Health Research Authority. <em>What approvals and decisions do I need?</em> Retrieved 11 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.hra.nhs.uk/approvals-amendments/what-approvals-do-i-need/" target="_blank">https://www.hra.nhs.uk/approvals-amendments/what-approvals-do-i-need/</a>
</p>
<p>Records Management Section, University of Edinburgh. <em>Research and the General Data Protection Regulation.</em> Last updated 14 November 2019.&nbsp;Retrieved 11 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/records-management/guidance/research/data-protection" target="_blank">https://www.ed.ac.uk/records-management/guidance/research/data-protection</a>
</p>
<p>Ritchie, F. (2019). <em>10 is the safest number that there&rsquo;s ever been.</em> Conference paper presented at Conference of European Statisticians, Netherlands 2019.
  <br />
  <a href="http://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/stats/documents/ece/ces/ge.46/2019/mtg1/SDC2019_S3_UK_Ritchie_AD.pdf" target="_blank">http://www.unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/stats/documents/ece/ces/ge.46/2019/mtg1/SDC2019_S3_UK_Ritchie_AD.pdf</a>
</p>
<p>Safe Data Access Professionals Working Group. (2019). <em>Handbook on Statistical Disclosure Control for Outputs </em>(PDF).
  <br />
  <a href="https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/media/622521/thf_datareport_aw_web.pdf" target="_blank">https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/media/622521/thf_datareport_aw_web.pdf</a>
</p>
<p>UK Data Service. <em>Anonymisation</em>. Retrieved 12 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ukdataservice.ac.uk/manage-data/legal-ethical/anonymisation.aspx" target="_blank">https://www.ukdataservice.ac.uk/manage-data/legal-ethical/anonymisation.aspx</a>
</p>
<p>UK Data Service. <em>Consent for data sharing.</em> Retrieved 12 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ukdataservice.ac.uk/manage-data/legal-ethical/consent-data-sharing" target="_blank">https://www.ukdataservice.ac.uk/manage-data/legal-ethical/consent-data-sharing</a>
</p>
]]></text></learningObject>
