<?xml version="1.0"?>
<learningObject language="en-GB" name="Preparing your data for archiving" navigation="Linear" textSize="12" displayMode="fill window" editorVersion="3" responsive="true"><bullets linkID="PG1590763393735" name="Learning objectives" delaySecs="1" showBullets="0" showPanel="0" panelWidth="Full"><![CDATA[<p>This unit introduces the key issues for researchers planning to&nbsp;archive and preserve their research data.
</p>
<p>&nbsp;
</p>
<p>After completing this unit you will:
</p>
<p>&nbsp;
</p>
<p>▪ Be aware of the importance of archiving&nbsp;research data effectively.
</p>
<p>▪ Understand what file formats are and how to select appropriate file formats to aid the long term preservation of your data.
</p>
<p>▪ Know what documentation you should keep to allow others to understand and use your data.
</p>
<p>▪ Be able to appraise your data and select the most appropriate data to archive.
</p>
<p>▪ Know the role of a digital repository and what you should consider when selecting a repository for archiving your data.
</p>
<p>▪ Appreciate how writing a thorough data management plan can help to ensure the archiving process is as simple and straightforward as possible.
</p>
]]></bullets><textGraphics linkID="PG1663945250101" name="Introduction" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/resizedpx-Books_in_public_library_damaged_in_2019_Sangli_flood.jpg'" tip="'Damaged library books' image from wikimedia commons (CC BY-SA)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>The research data you generate is irreplaceable, and planning ahead to ensure your data are&nbsp;managed appropriately during the collection, preparation and analysis stages of a research project is an essential part of the research process.</p>

<p>It is equally important that the research data you&rsquo;ve worked hard to produce is not somehow lost after your project ends because you neglected to take steps to ensure they&nbsp;remain&nbsp;accessible, understandable and usable to you and others in the longer term.</p>

<p>Archiving your data at the end of a project will ensure that a copy of your data are preserved for future reuse, either by you or other people. Planning ahead and&nbsp;choosing&nbsp;appropriate file formats, documenting your data effectively and finding a trusted data repository will all help to ensure your data will continue to be available and usable long after your research project has finished.</p>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1651570568573" name="Why archive your research data?"><![CDATA[<p>It is widely acknowledged that research data have value beyond their primary use to answer an initial set of research questions and produce accompanying research publications. Research funders now expect that data from publicly funded research will be shared, and publishers commonly require authors to make the data supporting their publications to be made available.</p>

<p>The benefits of sharing data extend beyond simply meeting the demands of a particular funder or publisher. Archiving your research data by depositing them with a trustworthy repository at the end of your project will also provide the following benefits:</p>

<ul>
	<li>ensure ongoing long-term access to your data</li>
	<li>make your research and publications more open, transparent and verifiable</li>
	<li>promote further research by enabling others to replicate and build on your work</li>
	<li>increase the impact of your research by allowing others to cite your data</li>
	<li>help protect the resource investment of public funders</li>
</ul>

<p>While it is possible to manage data sharing informally, for example by emailing a copy of your data whenever someone contacts you to request a copy, this is both time consuming and limits ongoing discoverability and access to your data by others.</p>

<p>Depositing your research data in a dedicated data archive or trusted data repository will facilitate its discovery and will also ensure the long-term preservation of your data for future access by you and other researchers.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1662478023534" name="Video: Benefits of sharing your research data"><![CDATA[<p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yhVqImna7cU?start=208" title="YouTube video player" width="560"></iframe></p>

<p>In this video clip, delegates of Research Waste / EQUATOR conference, University of Edinburgh September 2015, discuss the benefits of archiving and sharing their research data.</p>

<p>Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch the full video directly on&nbsp;<a href="https://youtu.be/yhVqImna7cU?t=208" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p>

<p>A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1662478579571" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Do you think data sharing helps to reduce waste and increase transparency of research?
</p>
<p>I guess this is another very obvious question and the answer must be yes because we produce tons of data which are basically just lost because no-one gets to know about it. Some of that data is useless because we&#39;re not always creating data that was guarded properly and so forth. But we have a lot of data which is extremely useful which goes into our reports , our papers, but it&#39;s usually not the original data, it&#39;s just means and so on, compound data. And so I think sharing the original data, which we write about, would be extremely helpful for others to extract additional information to answer questions that they might have which we didn&#39;t have and so forth. Also to check on the quality of our work. So sharing data, I think is another, in a way, no-brainer. But it&#39;s something that many researchers don&#39;t like to do.
</p>
<p>I&#39;m a big fan of data sharing, and re-use of data, because so much data is wasted. And so much research is then wasted. And it&#39;s not just to reduce waste. We have to remember it increases knowledge creation. I&#39;m more and more interested in this knowledge creation story because clinical trials are happening all over the world, and if you combine those data you get more efficient research and of course that&#39;s automatically reducing waste at the same time.
</p>
<p>Two areas where I&#39;ve used data sharing: One is individual patient systematic reviews, where you&#39;re doing a review of all the studies in one area. You can use the published data for that. But actually, it&#39;s more effort, but you can get a lot more done if you use the original data. But that requires a standardisation process, cleaning up process, so you&#39;ve got common outcomes etc.
</p>
<p>Second use of data sharing is to ask secondary questions. Quite a lot of the research I&#39;ve done has taken existing databases but asked new questions of those databases. Sometimes it&#39;s been trials that I&#39;ve been involved in personally. Sometimes it&#39;s getting datasets from other people to do that. But it means it&#39;s much easier to do that than to spend the hundreds of thousands if not sometimes millions of dollars or pounds in getting an original data set, that would have answered exactly the same question.
</p>
<p>What data sharing can achieve is the ability to answer a research question with the available data, when you don&#39;t need to go and gather any more to answer the question. So for example a systematic review of individual patient data meta-analysis of all the available data may successfully answer a research question without needing to get another research grant to go and collect more data.
</p>
<p>And does it help transparency then?
</p>
<p>What do you mean by &#39;Does it help transparency&#39;? Does it increase the transparency of research, this sharing of data? Well I think so. When you share data, you are exposing yourself to the need for external validation by another group of researchers. So they will always, they should always, seek to confirm that your data show what you said they showed when you published them initially.
</p>
<p>So I think you subject yourself to scrutiny. And I think making it an expectation of researchers also means that they are very careful in the way they collect and document their research in the first place, knowing that data sharing is one day ahead of them.
</p>]]></text><text linkID="PG1662371508215" name="What is archiving?"><![CDATA[<p>A data archive is more than just the infrastructure used to host a set of data, and a data repository will have a dedicated team that works with researchers and other data creators to receive data and take steps to preserve that information.</p>

<p>Of course, in addition to receiving and curating deposits a data archive also manages access to the archive for its users, ensuring that the data and information they provide access to are&nbsp;authentic, reliable and have&nbsp;integrity for future users.</p>

<p>In this sense, data archiving is not simply the act of depositing a dataset to a given repository but a process and series of activities by which deposited data are checked and curated to ensure:</p>

<ul>
	<li>submitted files can be opened and appropriate file formats were used to ensure the files will remain usable in the long term</li>
	<li>sufficient documentation is provided to ensure data can be understood and used by others</li>
	<li>datasets are&nbsp;described using appropriate metadata to ensure it is findable and identifiable.</li>
</ul>

<p>Taking steps to choose appropriate file formats and document&nbsp;your data effectively will ensure your data will still be useful long after your project ends, and&nbsp;will help make the process of archiving your data as simple and straightforward as possible.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1663683090416" name="Long-term data preservation"><![CDATA[<p>Preserving research data for future re-use can be particularly problematic due to the sheer amount being generated, as well as the wide variety and complexity of formats and types.</p>

<p>Unlike traditional &#39;hard copy&#39; objects such as books or publications where the user has unmediated access to the content, even the simplest piece of digital research data requires software to render it. Such environments evolve and change at a rapid pace, threatening the continuity of access to the data. Physical storage media, data formats, hardware, and software all become obsolete over time, posing significant threats to the survival of the content.</p>

<p>If you do not archive or manage your data in a systematic way, there is a real danger - and one that increases with the passage of time - that they will effectively be lost.</p>
]]></text><nav linkID="PG1664201549999" name="Steps to preserve your data" text="&lt;p&gt;There are a number of steps you can take during a research project that will make the process of archiving data at the end of a research project relatively simple and straightforward.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Click on the headings for more information.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Acc" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1664201618438" name="&lt;strong&gt;Create a thoughtful and thorough DMP&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Writing a data management plan (DMP) at the beginning of your project will help you to think about the different stages of data generation, storage and archiving. This&amp;nbsp;will help you to plan ahead and make sensible choices,&amp;nbsp;making the archiving process easier when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Please check the MANTRA unit &lt;strong&gt;Data management planning&lt;/strong&gt; for guidance on writing a DMP.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1664201628109" name="&lt;strong&gt;Store data using recommended formats&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Where possible, avoid using proprietary file formats which require specific licensed software to open, as this will help future proof your data and ensure that you data continue to be useful and usable in&amp;nbsp;the long term.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1664201639598" name="&lt;strong&gt;Keep detailed documentation&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;While you may fully understand your data while you are actively using it, with passing time it may become difficult to remember exactly how your data are structured, how your variables were generated, or the steps or procedures needed to actually open and use your data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Keeping suitable documentation detailing how your data were generated, how they were manipulated, and how they can be used will help to ensure that you and others are able to fully understand and use your data in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nav><nav linkID="PG1662388711903" name="File formats" text="&lt;p&gt;A file format is a way of encoding information within a computer file. A program or application must be able to recognise the file format in order to read the file and process the information within. For example, the HTML (hyper-text markup language) file format can be read and processed by a web browser to display web pages.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Click the grey buttons for more information about file formats.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Slide" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1662388736254" name="&lt;strong&gt;File extensions&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;File formats may be indicated by a file name extension, conventionally three or four letters following a dot in the filename that identifies the format (e.g. .jpg or .jpeg). However, depending on the operating system file extensions may be hidden or may not be used at all. For example, Windows systems allow you to display or hide file extensions, while files on Mac OS systems often do not use extensions at all which can present problems when using files created on a Mac on other systems.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1662388768183" name="&lt;strong&gt;Text vs binary formats&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Digital files may be either text or binary.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Text files are data structured as sequential lines of text and are encoded using a standard character set such as ASCII or Unicode.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Binary files can only be opened using software designed to read and process the relevant file format, and binary file formats may also be proprietary.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Unlike binary files, text files are human readable, are compatible with all operating systems, and can be easily read into different software packages. Further, many packages allow their binary data files to be converted to a text-format file which can be easily read into other programs.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For this reason, data saved in text file formats are the least likely to become obsolete over time, and are an ideal format for sharing and long-term preservation.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Some commonly used file extensions for saving plain text include .txt, .csv, .html, .json and .xml.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1662388795311" name="&lt;strong&gt;Open vs proprietary formats&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;File formats may be &lt;strong&gt;open &lt;/strong&gt;or &lt;strong&gt;proprietary &lt;/strong&gt;depending on whether the file specification detailing how a given file format is encoded has been made publicly available, and whether the given file format is free to use.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;A company or organisation developing a proprietary file format will commonly not publish the accompanying file specification, and use of a proprietary format often requires the use of specific licensed software. As a result, someone wishing to use a file saved in a proprietary format may not be able to open the file at all without paying for a licence to use the necessary software.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Open file formats are more likely to be readable by more than one specific application and without using licensed software because the accompanying file specification has been published, or the format has been licensed for use without charge. For example, Adobe PDF is an example of a proprietary file format that has become an open standard for encoding documents.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;There are many open file formats, including jpeg, png, flac, mp3, csv, html, json, gzip and zip.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nav><textGraphics linkID="PG1663669523740" name="(Digital) Appraisal" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/320px-Reality_check_ESA384313.jpg'" tip="'Virtual reality' image by the European Space Agency (ESA) on wikimedia (CC BY-SA 3.0)." transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>While simple text files may be opened by any text editor, opening and using other types of digital data may be more complicated depending on the software and&nbsp;hardware used to generate them, the file formats used, and any additional hardware that may be required to use the data.</p>

<p>At the most fundamental level, all digital information requires a combination of compatible hardware and software in order to open and use. Additionally, particular types of data may also necessitate the use of specific hardware devices or accessories.</p>

<p>Examples include,&nbsp;a compatible display to view 3D images or films, a motion controller to play a fitness video game on a games console, or a compatible headset and applicable devices necessary to view and interact with virtual reality environments.</p>

<p><strong>Significant Properties</strong></p>

<p>The archiving of digital data must therefore consider the contexts and characteristics of their ongoing use and re-use in terms of any specific software and hardware needed to open and use them.</p>

<p>When conducting digital appraisals, archivists will consider the essential characteristics required to interpret, render, and reuse a digital object, including:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Intellectual content, such as the text represented in the file</li>
	<li>Software stack, including applications, operating system, drivers, libraries, etc to render files</li>
	<li>Hardware or special devices to interact with digital objects such as a VR headset or video game controller</li>
</ul>
]]></textGraphics><textGraphics linkID="PG1663945553158" name="Digital obsolescence" align="Right" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/resized_dodo_300px.jpg'" tip="'Dodo reconstruction' image by Ballista from wikimedia commons (CC BY-SA)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Rapid changes in technology mean that file formats, software and hardware are all at risk of becoming obsolete over time. For example, ongoing updates to a software application may see support for file formats change, with new file formats supported and support for older formats dropped. This can cause issues when older data files are no longer supported by a later version of an application.
</p>
<p>File formats that are non-proprietary (e.g. open source), or in widespread use, will tend to retain the best chance of being readable in the future. Proprietary formats, especially non-standard formats that are used only by one particular application or only by a specific version of a software package, are most likely to present problems for ongoing usability over time.
</p>
<p>Data formats that conform to an agreed international standard are less likely to become obsolete, because a variety of software applications should be able to read them. For example, it may be possible to convert data saved in a proprietary format to a plain text format, such as csv, which will increase the likelihood it will remain usable in the long term. However, there are likely to be trade-offs in terms of software functionality when migrating data between file formats, for example formatting or macros which are available in the original proprietary format but may be lost when migrating to a different file format.
</p>
<p>Sometimes there is a <i>de facto</i> standard that is used; for example, PDF is an openly published portable document format invented by Adobe that has become a <i>de facto </i>standard for publishing documents online in a way that retains the original layout, fonts and text formatting.
</p>
]]></textGraphics><nav linkID="PG1663680487079" name="File format migration" text="&lt;p&gt;During your research you may need to convert or migrate your data files from one format to another. This may be due to a new computer, new software, sharing with someone who has different software, working on a shared platform instead of your own PC, or simply in order to ensure that your data can be read and used in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;When migrating data from one file format to another&amp;nbsp;you may find that&amp;nbsp;file sizes may change,&amp;nbsp;even becoming&amp;nbsp;surprisingly large. Further, there is a real&amp;nbsp;risk that information may be lost or that corruption of the original data may occur. It is important for you to understand what is at risk for the type of data you are working with.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;When saving your data in another format, it is worth reviewing information about the formats you are converting from and to before you begin.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Click on the buttons to see some of the potential risks when migrating different types of data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Button" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1663680874548" name="&lt;strong&gt;Word processed files&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Types of information that may potentially be lost during migration...&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;fonts&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;text formatting&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;headers&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;footers&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;footnotes&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;links to other documents.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663680931347" name="&lt;strong&gt;Numeric files&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Types of information that may potentially be lost during migration...&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;special characters (such as tabs)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;end of line returns&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;last characters in rows (due to row size limitations)&amp;nbsp;especially blanks used as a missing data code&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;last rows (due to row number limitations).&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663681002828" name="&lt;strong&gt;Database files&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Types of information that may potentially be lost during migration...&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;special characters&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;end of line returns&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;last characters in rows&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;last rows&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;relations among items in a table and among tables.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663681179388" name="&lt;strong&gt;Image files&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Types of information that may potentially be lost during migration...&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;loss of layers&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;colour fidelity&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;resolution&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663681263875" name="&lt;strong&gt;Multimedia files&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Types of information that may potentially be lost during migration...&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;colour fidelity&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;resolution&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;frame rates&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;sound quality&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;codecs and wrappers&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/></nav><textGraphics linkID="PG1663677632643" name="Data compression" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/Compression.artifacts.jpg'" tip="'Compression artifacts' image from Wikimedia Commons (CC0)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>At some point you may choose to compress your data files, for the purpose of local or networked storage, transportation or for ease of sharing. Compression is a method of&nbsp;bit-rate reduction, which involves encoding information using fewer bits than the original representation.</p>

<p>Zip (.zip) is a <i>de facto</i> standard compression format that is used on Windows, Macintosh, Linux and Unix platforms, though there are others, sometimes specific to a particular operating system. A self-executing zip file (.exe) should not be used if the file is to be decompressed on another operating system.</p>

<p>Zip is a &quot;lossless&quot; type of compression, which means the file should be identical to the original once unzipped. There are also &quot;lossy&quot; types of compression associated with some multimedia file formats, which may result in some distortion or loss of quality/fidelity when played or displayed.</p>

<p>Tar (tape archive) files are commonly used in Unix / Linux to bundle a set of files into one. Tar files may also be zipped to reduce the filesize (.tar.Z or tar.gz or .tar.bz2). In Windows environments the zip file can be used for the same purpose - to bundle files together, with or without compression, or with more or less compression. Utilities for tar files in Windows also exist.</p>

<p>Lossiness can be one trade-off of compression. Another is the processing time it takes to compress/decompress before or during use, or the amount of computing resource this takes, in the case of very large files or shared servers.</p>
]]></textGraphics><textGraphics linkID="PG1663682035675" name="Checking the integrity of migrated files" align="Right" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/fileformats.png'" tip="'File formats' image from www.digitalbevaring.dk (CC-BY 2.5)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>When migrating data between formats, including when extracting a previously compressed archive file, it is essential that you check the integrity of converted files as thoroughly as possible immediately afterwards, e.g. by checking that the file size is as expected, checking the file has the correct number of rows and columns, testing functionality, as well as simply &#39;eyeballing&#39; the data to check that it looks as it should.</p>

<p>When you reach the point of submitting your data to an archive, a&nbsp;repository will have its own criteria and procedures to verify&nbsp;the quality of the submitted data. For example, checksum algorithm tools&nbsp;are commonly used to allow verification that a digital file has&nbsp;not become corrupted when being copied from one location to another (e.g. when downloading a copy of a data file to your computer&nbsp;from a repository).</p>
]]></textGraphics><nav linkID="PG1663678712455" name="Documenting your data" text="&lt;p&gt;Digital data by definition must be machine-readable. However, all researchers need to understand how their data were generated, as well as any steps taken to manipulate and prepare the data for analysis, to be sure that the outputs generated from their data are valid. Therefore, one cannot overestimate the importance of effectively documenting such procedures and steps.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Documentation should ideally provide sufficiently detailed information about how raw data were collected, how data were manipulated and cleaned, how measures were derived, and how any outputs from the data were generated. This is especially true if your research is going to be part of the scholarly record.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Remember, good documention will make your data easier to use for both your own future use and for others.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Col" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1663678731133" name="&lt;b&gt;For your own benefit&lt;/b&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;You may be on intimate terms with your dataset while you are collecting and analysing it, but remembering that the variable &amp;quot;sglmemgp&amp;quot; means single member of group, or the exact method you used to specify or derive a specific variable, becomes increasingly difficult months or years later.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663678758061" name="&lt;strong&gt;For the benefit of other people&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons other people may want to examine or use your data - to understand your methods, to verify your findings, to review your submitted publication, to replicate your research, to design a similar study, or even to archive your data for access and re-use by others.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Good documentation is therefore critical to enable someone to understand and use your data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nav><text linkID="PG1663926214986" name="Video: The importance of documenting data"><![CDATA[<p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pQFWZV8g3jU?start=80&amp;end=155" title="YouTube video player" width="560"></iframe></p>

<p>In this clip, Dr Bert Remijsen talks about the importance of documenting his research data effectively to enable others to use them in the future.</p>

<p>Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch the full video directly on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pQFWZV8g3jU&amp;feature=share&amp;utm_source=EJGixIgBCJiu2KjB4oSJEQ" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p>

<p>A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1663931963982" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>When you are investigating a minority language as I&#39;m doing research on it is sparse so that the next researcher investigating the language in-depth well that might be in fifty years&#39; time that might be in a hundred years&#39; time. So that because the rate here is so slow then documenting each phase of research of the languages is very important.</p>

<p>So you have fields where there is a very intense turnover and progression and then yeah then there is a lot of kind of the memory of where the field of research is is shared by lots of people. In this case that&#39;s not the case. So .. for the state of the art to progress I need to document very well what I find so that later on the next set / team of researchers can start from where I left off. It&#39;s often more sequential perhaps than concurrent research, on minority languages.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1663945737332" name="Levels of documentation"><![CDATA[<p>Research data need to be documented at various levels:</p>

<ul>
	<li><b>Project level</b>: what the study set out to do, how it contributes new knowledge to the field, what the research questions/hypotheses were, what methodologies were used, what sampling frames were used, what instruments and measures were used, etc. A complete academic thesis normally contains this information in detail, but a published article may not. If a dataset is shared, a detailed technical report will need to be included for the user to understand how the data were collected and processed. You should also provide a sample bibliographic citation to indicate how you would like secondary users of your data to cite it in any publications, etc.</li>
	<br />
	<li><b>File or database level</b>: how all the files (or tables in a database) that make up the dataset relate to each other; what format they are in; whether they supercede or are superceded by previous files. A readme.txt file is the classic way of accounting for all the files and folders in a project.</li>
	<br />
	<li><b>Variable or item level</b>: the key to understanding research results is knowing exactly how an object of analysis came about. Not just, for example, a variable name at the top of a spreadsheet file, but the full label explaining the meaning of that variable in terms of how it was operationalised.</li>
</ul>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1663945670406" name="Types of data documentation" align="Right" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/DataDictionary_resized_300.png'" tip="'Data dictionary' image by Ethacke1 from wikimedia commons (CC BY-SA)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Some examples of data documentation include:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>laboratory notebooks &amp; experimental protocols</li>
  <br />
  <li>questionnaires, codebooks, data dictionaries</li>
  <br />
  <li>software syntax and output files</li>
  <br />
  <li>information about equipment settings &amp; instrument calibration</li>
  <br />
  <li>database schema</li>
  <br />
  <li>methodology reports</li>
  <br />
  <li>provenance information about sources of derived or digitised data</li>
</ul>]]></textGraphics><textGraphics linkID="PG1664182487928" name="Documentation example: Laboratory notebooks" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/640px-Lab_Notebook.jpg'" tip="'Lab notebook' image by Katherine Stember from wikimedia commons (CC-BY 4.0)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>For laboratory researchers, laboratory notebooks are a central component of data management and the research process, and it is becoming increasingly common practice for labs to use electronic lab notebooks to maintain records of lab work digitally, rather than traditional lab notebooks composed of handwritten notation.</p>

<p>Regardless of whether records are analogue or digital, laboratory notebooks play an important role in supporting claims relating to intellectual property developed by University researchers, and may even be relied upon to defend claims of scientific fraud.</p>

<p>In less extreme circumstances, they demonstrate adherence to standards of good practice, academic and ethical integrity, and compliance with contractual provisions permitting sponsors to audit work carried out in pursuit of sponsored-research.</p>

<p>For these reasons, thorough and effective management of laboratory data and the routine documentation of all lab procedures is a highly important responsibility for all laboratory researchers.</p>

<p>There is more information about electronic lab notebooks in the MANTRA unit <strong>Organising data</strong>, and in the &#39;Further reading&#39; section at the end of this unit.</p>
]]></textGraphics><nav linkID="PG1664189468329" name="Describing your data using metadata" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What is metadata?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;The term metadata is commonly defined as &amp;quot;data about data,&amp;quot; information that describes or contextualises the data. The difference between documentation and metadata is that the first is meant to be read by humans and the second implies computer-processing (though metadata may also be human-readable).&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;Documentation is sometimes considered a form of metadata, because it is information about data, and when it is very structured it can be. The importance of metadata lies in the potential for machine-to-machine interoperability, providing the user with added functionality, or &amp;#39;actionable&amp;#39; information.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;There are three broad categories of metadata - click on the buttons for more information about each.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Tab" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}" hidePage="false"><navPage linkID="PG1664189485664" name="&lt;b&gt;Descriptive&lt;/b&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Common fields such as title, author, abstract, and keywords which help users to discover online resources through searching and browsing.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1664189506528" name="&lt;b&gt;Administrative&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;" text="&lt;p&gt;May include information about preservation, rights management, and technical information about formats.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1664189552680" name="&lt;b&gt;Structural&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;" text="&lt;p&gt;How different components of a set of associated data relate to one another, such as how a dataset relates to another dataset, or a published paper.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1664189696407" name="&lt;strong&gt;SUMMARY&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Metadata are important, particularly when data are shared online. Metadata help to place your dataset in a broader context, allowing those outside your institution, discipline, or software environment to understand how to interpret your data.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Your data management plan should help determine whether you need to apply metadata descriptors or tags at some point during your project.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;"/></nav><nav linkID="PG1663935902979" name="Deciding what data to keep" text="&lt;p&gt;When planning to archive our data we will need to make decisions about what data needs to be&amp;nbsp;archived and for how long. For example, there may be a legal reason&amp;nbsp;or a data collection policy stipulating&amp;nbsp;that data be kept for a specified amount of time, or a&amp;nbsp;funder may&amp;nbsp;require data from a project be retained for a specified time after a project ends.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Appraisal criteria can help you to decide what should be kept, how long to keep it, when you should review whether you want to continue&amp;nbsp;keeping it, and what information that you might very deliberately want to destroy.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The following slides outline one approach to appraising data, taken from the Digital Curation Centre&amp;#39;s &amp;#39;Five steps to decide what data to keep: a checklist for appraising research data&amp;#39;, which&amp;nbsp;can help you to answer these questions.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Click on the grey arrow buttons to progress to the next slide.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Slide" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1663936026039" name="What data and for how long?" text="&lt;p&gt;When considering what to keep you should consider what types of data are suitable for reuse:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source data&lt;/strong&gt;; data collected, created, or held elsewhere that the research has used&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assembled datasets&lt;/strong&gt;; data extracted or derived from (1) above&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Referenced data&lt;/strong&gt;; data reworking a subset of (2) above in order to take the analysis further or draw conclusions. Consistent with whatever is considered &amp;lsquo;supplementary material&amp;rsquo; to research findings in your domain.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;You should consult the data management policies of your funder, institution, or other relevant organisation&amp;nbsp;to determine how long applicable data should be kept. Where appropriate this could be assessed periodically.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663935925977" name="Step 1. Identify purposes that the data could fulfil" text="&lt;p&gt;Consider the purpose or &amp;lsquo;reuse case&amp;rsquo; that the data could serve beyond the research context in which it was created or collected:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Verification by others&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Further analysis&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Building academic reputation&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Community resource development (e.g., a reference dataset, methods test-bed, or domain database)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Further publications&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Learning &amp;amp; teaching&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Future private use&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663935936240" name="Step 2. Identify data that must be kept" text="&lt;p&gt;Generally the decision on what must be kept will depend on the data creators priorities, but the decision will also need to account for legal, regulatory or policy compliance issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Are there Research Data Policy reasons to keep it?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Do regulations require the data to be available?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Are there other legal or contractual reasons?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Does it contain personal data relevant to the reuse purpose?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663935945312" name="Step 3. Identify data that should be kept" text="&lt;p&gt;Bearing in mind the potential reuse purposes, consider the following criteria to help decide which data should be retained and for what reason.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Are data quality and documentation good enough?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Is there likely to be a demand?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;How difficult is it to replicate?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Do any barriers to further use exist? For example, are data sensitive, will file formats restrict data use by others, is specialist software needed to use the data?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Is it the only copy?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1663935961420" name="Step 4. Weigh up the costs" text="&lt;p&gt;It is important to account for all data management costs which will impact on your research commitments and your organisation&amp;rsquo;s budgetary constraints.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Is funding available to pay data management costs arising during the research, including those of preparing the data for archiving?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Is funding available to pay any charges for storage and curation beyond the research period?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;When working out the accumulated cost of managing your data across the lifetime of&amp;nbsp;a project you should consider all previous, ongoing&amp;nbsp;and future costs relating to&amp;nbsp;staff time, equipment/hardware, or software and service charges for the following key activities:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Creation, collection &amp;amp; cleaning&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Short-term storage &amp;amp; backup&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Short-term access &amp;amp; security&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Team communication &amp;amp; development&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Preservation &amp;amp; long-term access&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/></nav><text linkID="PG1664189979577" name="The importance of data citation"><![CDATA[<p>As every scholar knows, in the course of publishing research it is essential to cite one&#39;s sources. The reference list at the end of a publication is crucial to establishing the credibility of the author&#39;s claims, as well as the provenance of a particular theory or school of thought.</p>

<p>This is no less true for datasets than for publications. Correctly citing the data that you use, and getting credit when others make use of your own data, is therefore an important part of the academic record.</p>

<p>Data citation:</p>

<ul>
	<li>follows good scholarly practice of acknowledging the work of others</li>
	<li>provides a structure that recognises&nbsp;and&nbsp;rewards data creators</li>
	<li>supports reproducibility and promotes openess in research practice</li>
	<li>simplifies the process of identifying,&nbsp;finding&nbsp;and accessing relevant research data</li>
	<li>enables funders to track reuse,&nbsp;measure impact and demonstrate value of publicly funded research</li>
</ul>

<p>Taken from UK Data Service. <i>Reasons to cite data correctly</i>. Retrieved 26th September 2022&nbsp;from http://ukdataservice.ac.uk/</p>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1663342651792" name="Trustworthy Digital Repositories" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/cropped-cropped-CoreTrustSeal-logo-150px.jpg'" tip="CoreTrustSeal logo" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>When choosing a data repository you need to be sure that your data will be curated and managed appropriately over time. Choosing a repository that has been certified will help you to be confident that the repository you choose is trustworthy and your data will remain findable, accessible and usable in the future.</p>

<p>Several certification standards have been developed which allow the principles and practices of digital repositories to be evaluated.</p>

<p>Some examples of certification standards for digital repositories include:</p>

<ul>
	<li>CoreTrustSeal - a peer-reviewed certification standard that evaluates data repositories against a set of specific criteria.</li>
	<li>&#39;Audit and certification of trustworthy digital repositories&#39; (ISO 16363)</li>
	<li>&#39;Criteria for Trustworthy Digital Archives&#39; (DIN 31644).</li>
</ul>

<p>The repository community has also established a set of principles called &#39;TRUST: defining best practice through transparency, responsibility, user focus, sustainability, and technology&#39; which help promote ongoing preservation standards and practice among the repository community.</p>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1663942239893" name="FAIR data sharing"><![CDATA[<p>It is now an expectation that publicly funded research data should be made openly available as soon as possible with as few restrictions as necessary.</p>

<p>Thinking about the file formats you use, the documentation you keep, and the metadata you use to describe your data will all help to make your data FAIR (findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable).</p>

<p>Principal investigators, research staff and research students planning to archive their data should consider how they can best make their data FAIR when writing their data management plans:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Think about long-term accessibility</li>
	<li>Think about long-term sustainability</li>
	<li>Use standard preservation formats when possible</li>
</ul>

<p>Links to relevant publications, people, projects, and other research products such as software or source code should be provided in metadata records, with persistent identifiers when available.</p>

<p>Discoverability and access by machines is considered as important as access by humans. Standard open licences should be applied to data and code deposits.</p>

<p>You can find more information about the FAIR principles, data repositories and sharing research data in the MANTRA unit <strong>FAIR sharing and access</strong>.</p>

<p>If your data are not suitable for FAIR sharing under an open license, you will need to consider an archive providing appropriate access controls necessary to manage and restrict access to the data for as long as is needed. You can find more information on managing sensitive research data in the MANTRA unit <strong>Protecting sensitive data</strong>.</p>
]]></text><hotspotImage linkID="PG1664203977160" name="DataShare - an example of an open data repository" text="&lt;p&gt;The Edinburgh DataShare is an institutional data repository&amp;nbsp; which provides researchers from the University of Edinburgh a way to archive and share their research data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The image shows an example of an item that has been archived with DataShare. Click on the arrows to find out more about how you and your chosen data repository can help to&amp;nbsp;make your research data FAIR.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" url="FileLocation + 'media/DataShare_item_page_example_v2.PNG'" tip="An example of a dataset submitted to Edinburgh DataShare" interactivity="Show Me" highlight="false" hicol="0xFFFF00" align="Left" nextTxt="Next" priorTxt="Previous"><hotspot linkID="PG1664203977171" name="Descriptive metadata: Title" text="&lt;p&gt;Your dataset should be given an appropriate&amp;nbsp;title which allows anyone searching for or accessing this dataset to understand what the data are about.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" x="6" y="54" w="690" h="67"/><hotspot linkID="PG1664203977173" name="Citation" text="&lt;p&gt;Anyone using&amp;nbsp;data created by another person should acknowledge their work&amp;nbsp;appropriately.&amp;nbsp;A data repository will commonly provide a suggested citation which should be used by anyone wishing to use and cite the data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" x="238" y="130" w="453" h="89"/><hotspot linkID="PG1664204325840" name="Descriptive metadata: Description" text="&lt;p&gt;A key part of the metadata record, the dataset description should provide sufficient information for others to understand what the data are&amp;nbsp;and what they can be used for.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" x="236" y="224" w="464" h="82"/><hotspot linkID="PG1664204270833" name="Administrative and structural metadata" text="&lt;p&gt;You should use metadata to describe your data following the metadata schema of the repository or archive. Metadata provide machine readable and human readable information about the data, enabling&amp;nbsp;data to be found using online search tools&amp;nbsp;and to be understood by prospective users.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" x="5" y="211" w="234" h="316"/><hotspot linkID="PG1664204390527" name="Submit&amp;nbsp;data files in appropriate file formats" text="&lt;p&gt;When submitting data to a repository you should choose appropriate file formats to avoid potential issues in the long term use of your data. An&amp;nbsp;archive or repository may review submitted data files to ensure they meet&amp;nbsp;it&amp;#39;s requirements. You may be asked to convert&amp;nbsp;files to another format for preservation purposes, for example migrating files from a proprietary format to a plain text file format where this is appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" x="240" y="350" w="386" h="137"/><hotspot linkID="PG1664204439848" name="Provide documentation" text="&lt;p&gt;You should provide appropriate documentation to support others wishing to reuse your data. This may include information about any file structure and file types included in the dataset&amp;nbsp;along with any additional information needed to make use of the data. This information may be provided&amp;nbsp;in a readme.txt file alongside the data files, as in this example.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" x="238" y="483" w="422" h="30"/><hotspot linkID="PG1664204497288" name="Selecting a license" text="&lt;p&gt;You need to share your data under a license in order to permit others to use it. A copy of the license should be included alongside the files themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For example, DataShare users are recommended to license their data under an open&amp;nbsp;CC-BY license which allows data to be reused for any purpose with the only restriction being that the data and the original data creators are cited, for example by using the suggested citation.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" x="236" y="527" w="153" h="33"/></hotspotImage><text linkID="PG1663927722860" name="Video: Archiving research data"><![CDATA[<p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zK1Tp0dvahU?start=36&amp;end=142" title="YouTube video player" width="560"></iframe></p>

<p>In this video clip, Dr Bert Remijsen speaks about some of the reasons and benefits of archiving research data.</p>

<p>Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch the full video directly on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zK1Tp0dvahU&amp;feature=share&amp;utm_source=EJGixIgBCJiu2KjB4oSJEQ" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p>

<p>A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1663929266810" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>In the process of doing research a wide range of data gets created. In my case a lot of that is sound data. That will be songs. That will be narratives. That will be the results of controlled studies where you get little sound clips of for example a hundred from ten speakers so like a thousand in total. I do acoustic analysis on. And while the project is ongoing all of those research data ... the key issue is making backups.
</p>
<p>But when a project is completed and the thing is to archive and to make the data publicly available and I do that primarily through Edinburgh DataShare which has a user-friendly interface to upload data yourself and that data then and that data then becomes available to anybody making it possible to reach users that you can imagine and beyond ... the people you are thinking of.
</p>
<p>When it comes to the sharing of data depending on the nature of the output there are very different stakeholders to whom it&#39;s relevant so when it is a very much a scientific study then I can make a dataset available so that other linguists can use it to investigate language phenomena and answer research questions that I haven&#39;t thought of myself at all.
</p>
]]></text><gapFill linkID="PG1663924952578" name="Summary (1&amp;nbsp;of 3)" text="&lt;p&gt;You have now been introduced to the key considerations and challenges for researchers wishing to archive&amp;nbsp;and preserve research data in the long term.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;As a summary task please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the gaps left in the text.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;b&gt;Hint:&lt;/b&gt; If the word you select is not the correct word you won&amp;#39;t be able to drop it into the gap.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" passage="&lt;p&gt;A file |format| encodes information in a computer file, enabling another program to access data within it. HTML and PDF are two examples of commonly used file formats and may be identified by the filename suffixes |.html| and |.pdf| respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;Files are based on either text or |binary| encoding; the former is both machine- and human-readable and the latter only readable by means of appropriate software. Thus |text| files are less likely to become obsolete. Examples of file name extensions for text files are .txt and |.csv|.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;If you need to convert or migrate your data files from one format to another, you need to be aware of the potential risk of the loss or |corruption| of your data and take appropriate steps to avoid/minimise it.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Well done! Please continue to the next part of the activity on the next screen.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Large" checkBtn="Check" showBtn="Show Answers" gapFillWrong="You have not filled in any answers correctly. Please try again." gapFillWrongTracking="You have not filled in any answers correctly." gapFillIncomplete="Please complete the exercise." gapFillPartWrongTracking="Your correct answers are shown in green." gapFillPartWrong="Your correct answers are shown in green. Try again with those you have got wrong."/><gapFill linkID="PG1663924697283" name="Summary (2&amp;nbsp;of 3)" text="" passage="&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why you need to document your data:&lt;br /&gt;&#10;- to |help| you remember the details later&lt;br /&gt;&#10;- to help others understand your research, verify your |findings|, |review| your submitted publication, |replicate| your results, or even |archive| your data for access and |re-use|.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The term |metadata| is commonly defined as data about data. Metadata is commonly both |machine|-readable and human-readable. The three types of metadata are: descriptive, |administrative|, and structural.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Well done! Please continue to the last&amp;nbsp; part of the activity on the next screen.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Large" checkBtn="Check" showBtn="Show Answers" gapFillWrong="You have not filled in any answers correctly. Please try again." gapFillWrongTracking="You have not filled in any answers correctly." gapFillIncomplete="Please complete the exercise." gapFillPartWrongTracking="Your correct answers are shown in green." gapFillPartWrong="Your correct answers are shown in green. Try again with those you have got wrong."/><gapFill linkID="PG1664200146616" name="Summary (3&amp;nbsp;of 3)" text="" passage="&lt;p&gt;A data repository provides both the |infrastructure| to store data and the procedures to ensure data:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;can be |read| and use file formats that will remain |usable| in the future&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;have sufficient |documentation| to ensure they can be understood and used by others&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;are described using appropriate |metadata| to ensure they are findable and |identifiable|&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! You have successfully completed this unit.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Medium" checkBtn="Check" showBtn="Show Answers" gapFillWrong="You have not filled in any answers correctly. Please try again." gapFillWrongTracking="You have not filled in any answers correctly." gapFillIncomplete="Please complete the exercise." gapFillPartWrongTracking="Your correct answers are shown in green." gapFillPartWrong="Your correct answers are shown in green. Try again with those you have got wrong."/><text linkID="PG1661258767366" name="Next &amp; further reading"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What to do next?</strong>
</p>
<p>You have now completed this unit. Take a look at the &#39;Further reading&#39; where you will find a list of resources that will help you gain further understanding of file formats, data archiving and preservation.
</p>
<p>You could also start a new unit and come back to check these resources later. We recommend that you continue with the <a href="../keepingresearchdatasafe/" target="_blank">Keeping research data safe</a> unit.
</p>
<p>If you prefer, you can also go back to the <a href="http://mantra.ed.ac.uk/">MANTRA</a> home page and choose a different unit.
</p>
<p>
  <br />
  <strong>Further reading</strong>
</p>
<p>Borghi J, Abrams S, Lowenberg D, Simms S, Chodacki J. (2018). Support Your Data: A Research Data Management Guide for Researchers. Research Ideas and Outcomes 4: e26439.
  <br />
  <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.4.e26439" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.4.e26439</a>
</p>
<p>Bungers, S. (2022) The Electronic Lab Notebook in 2022: A comprehensive guide - How to choose the best ELN for your research.&nbsp;Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.labfolder.com/electronic-lab-notebook-eln-research-guide/" target="_blank">https://www.labfolder.com/electronic-lab-notebook-eln-research-guide/</a>
</p>
<p>Cornell University. Guide to writing &quot;readme&quot; style metadata. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://data.research.cornell.edu/content/readme" target="_blank">https://data.research.cornell.edu/content/readme</a>
</p>
<p>Digital Curation Centre. (2014). <em>&#39;Five steps to decide what data to keep: a checklist for appraising research data v.1&#39;</em>. Edinburgh: Digital Curation Centre. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.dcc.ac.uk/guidance/how-guides/five-steps-decide-what-data-keep" target="_blank">https://www.dcc.ac.uk/guidance/how-guides/five-steps-decide-what-data-keep</a>
</p>
<p>Digital Preservation Coalition. <em>Technology Watch Publications</em>. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.dpconline.org/digipres/discover-good-practice/tech-watch-reports" target="_blank">https://www.dpconline.org/digipres/discover-good-practice/tech-watch-reports</a>
</p>
<p>Digital Preservation Coalition. <em>Digital Preservation Handbook, 2nd Edition</em>. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.dpconline.org/handbook" target="_blank">https://www.dpconline.org/handbook</a>
</p>
<p>Library of Congress. <em>Resource Description &amp; Access (RDA) Metadata Guidance Documentation</em>. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.loc.gov/aba/rda/mgd/" target="_blank">https://www.loc.gov/aba/rda/mgd/</a>
</p>
<p>Library of Congress. <em>Sustainability Factors</em>. Sustainability of Digital Formats: Planning of Library of Congress Collections. Last updated 01 May 2017. Retrieved August 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/sustain/sustain.shtml" target="_blank">https://www.loc.gov/preservation/digital/formats/sustain/sustain.shtml</a>
</p>
<p>PLOS. (2019). Building Trust to Break Down Barriers. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://theplosblog.plos.org/2019/10/building-trust-to-break-down-barriers/" target="_blank">https://theplosblog.plos.org/2019/10/building-trust-to-break-down-barriers/</a>
</p>
<p>UK Data Service. <em>The importance of managing and sharing data: Document your data</em>. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/learning-hub/research-data-management/#document-your-data" target="_blank">https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/learning-hub/research-data-management/#document-your-data</a>
</p>
<p>University of Edinburgh, Research Data Service. Choose the best file formats. Retrieved September 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/information-services/research-support/research-data-service/after/data-repository/choosing-file-formats" target="_blank">https://www.ed.ac.uk/information-services/research-support/research-data-service/after/data-repository/choosing-file-formats</a>
</p>
]]></text></learningObject>
