<?xml version="1.0"?>
<learningObject language="en-GB" name="File formats and transformation" navigation="Linear" textSize="12" displayMode="fill window" editorVersion="3" responsive="true"><bullets linkID="PG1590763393735" name="Learning objectives" delaySecs="1" showBullets="0" showPanel="0" panelWidth="Full"><![CDATA[<p>This unit introduces you to the concepts of data file formatting, compression, normalisation, and other kinds of data transformation and why they are useful.</p>

<p><br />
After completing this unit you will:</p>

<p><br />
▪ Understand why research data formatting and transformation is important.</p>

<p>▪ Know how to make decisions about data file formatting, compression, normalisation and other transformations.</p>

<p>▪ Use the information featured in the course to improve your research data management practice.</p>
]]></bullets><bleedingImage linkID="PG1590763499039" name="Introduction to file formats" align="Left" url="FileLocation + 'media/Windows-8-like-files-icons.png'" tip="Windows file format icons" imagesize="auto" addmargin="true"><![CDATA[<p>A file format is a way of encoding information within a computer file. A program or application must be able to recognise the file format in order to access data within the file.<br />
<br />
For example, a web browser is able to process and display a file in the HTML (hyper-text markup language) file format so that it appears as a Web page. If the browser encounters another filetype, it may need to call on a special plug-in to view it, or it may simply let you download the file to view in another program if it cannot recognise it.<br />
<br />
A particular file format is often indicated as part of a file&#39;s name by a file name extension, or suffix. Conventionally, the extension follows a dot in the filename and contains three or four letters that identify the format (.jpg or .jpeg).<br />
<br />
In the Windows operating systems you can choose whether to display file suffixes or not. Windows 10, for example, has a&nbsp;&#39;File name extensions&#39; option within&nbsp;the View menu of the file browser. Macintosh files often do not have a suffix, which can be problematic when copying files to a different&nbsp;system to use.<br />
<br />
Files in proprietary formats usually must be opened by the software in which they were created. Someone without a licence to the software may not be able to open the file at all.</p>

<p>Open formats, in which the software company or collective publishes the format rather than keeps it proprietary, are more likely to be readable by more than one application. Adobe PDF is an example of an open format that may be viewed in a number of applications, not just Adobe products.</p>
]]></bleedingImage><bleedingImage linkID="PG1590763834382" name="Text vs binary formats" align="Right" url="FileLocation + 'media/excel_export_file_formats.png'" tip="Alternative file formats available in Excel" imagesize="auto" addmargin="true"><![CDATA[<p>File types are based on either text or binary encoding.
  <br />
  <br />
  <strong>Text files</strong> are machine-readable through a character encoding standard such as ASCII or Unicode. <strong>Binary files </strong>can only be read by applicable software, and may be proprietary. Only binary formats can be executed. Some files may contain both binary and text.
  <br />
  <br />
  A great advantage of creating or saving research data in a text format, where possible, is that such files can be read in by a plain text editor, such as Windows Notepad, and are human readable. They can be opened in any operating system, and by a wide range of applications. Therefore, text files are the most unlikely to become obsolete over time, and are a good format for sharing and long-term preservation.
  <br />
  <br />
  Some commonly used file extensions for saving plain text files include .txt, .csv, .html, .json and .xml.
  <br />
  <br />
  Most software applications offer export or exchange formats that allow a text-formatted file to be created for importing into another program.
  <br />
  <br />
  For example, Microsoft Excel allows spreadsheet data to be saved in a number of alternative formats (shown in image) using the 'Save As' command. These include comma delimited and tab delimited formats, allowing the 'row x column' structure of data to be preserved. However, each worksheet must be saved as a separate file, and any text formatting or macros in the native format will be lost on conversion.
</p>]]></bleedingImage><gapFill linkID="PG1590766898895" name="Activity - File formats" text="&lt;p&gt;Fill in the missing word to identify the relevant file format being described.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" passage="&lt;p&gt;A file format used to store multiple cells, usually in two-dimensional matrix or grid consisting of rows and columns. |spreadsheet|&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This file format type is used to store digital images. |graphic|&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This file format is usually rendered and supported by just one software application or software company. |proprietary|&#10;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This file format is used to store markup language for creating web pages. |html|&#10;&lt;/p&gt;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;Well done, you have selected all the correct answers!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Full" checkBtn="Check" showBtn="Show Answers" gapFillWrong="You have not filled in any answers correctly. Please try again." gapFillWrongTracking="You have not filled in any answers correctly." gapFillIncomplete="Please complete the exercise." gapFillPartWrongTracking="Your correct answers are shown in green." gapFillPartWrong="Your correct answers are shown in green. Try again with those you have got wrong." noise="open video excel"/><bleedingImage linkID="PG1590768399757" name="File format obsolescence &amp;amp; standards" align="Left" url="FileLocation + 'media/Sony_Walkman_by_splorp_on_flickr_CC-BY-NC-ND.jpg'" tip="Sony Walkman" imagesize="auto" addmargin="true"><![CDATA[<p>File formats that are non-proprietary (e.g. open source), or in widespread use, will tend to retain the best chance of being readable in the future. Proprietary formats, especially non-standard formats, used only by a specific software program or specific software version, are likely to present problems for future use.<br />
<br />
Rapid changes in technology and the market mean that file formats can become obsolete quickly - often a software application is unable to read a file created by an earlier version of itself. The implications for research data management depend on how long data need to be retained for future use - your own or others&#39;.<br />
<br />
Data formats that conform to an agreed international standard are less likely to become obsolete, because a variety of software applications should be able to read them. However, there are likely to be trade-offs in terms of software functionality, for example loss of formatting or macros.<br />
<br />
Sometimes there is a <i>de facto</i> standard that is used; for example, PDF, an openly published portable document format invented by Adobe, has become a <i>de facto</i> standard for publishing documents on the World Wide Web in a way that retains the original layout, fonts and text formatting.</p>
]]></bleedingImage><textGraphics linkID="PG1596031316942" name="Long-term data preservation: the risk of loss" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/StorageMedia_DigitalPreservation.png'" tip="Storage media image by J&#xF8;rgen Stamp (digitalbevaring.dk, CC-BY)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Preserving research data for future re-use can be particularly problematic due to the sheer amount being generated as well as the wide variety and complexity of formats and types.</p>

<p>Unlike traditional &#39;hardcopy&#39; objects such as books or publications where the user has unmediated access to the content even the simplest piece of digital research data requries software to render it. Such environments evolve and change at a rapid pace, threatening the continuity of access to the data. Physical storage media, data formats, hardware, and software all become obsolete over time, posing significant threats to the survival of the content.</p>

<p>If you do not archive or manage your data in a systematic way, there is a real danger - and one that increases with the passage of time - that they will effectively be lost.</p>
]]></textGraphics><quiz linkID="PG1596039204044" name="Activity 1 - Data loss" order="random" numQuestions="*" align="left" panelWidth="Medium" instructions="&lt;p&gt;Given the issues raised in this unit so far, consider the following questions about select the term which best decribes the given scenario.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" judge="true" showfeedback="true" feedback="&lt;p&gt;wel done, that&amp;#39;s the end of the quiz.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" quesCount="Question {i} of {n}" feedbackLabel="Feedback" singleRight="Your answer is correct!" singleWrong="Your answer is incorrect" multiRight="You have selected all the correct answers" multiWrong="You have not selected the correct combination of answers" onCompletion="You have completed the exercise" score="You scored {i} / {n}" submitBtnText="Submit" nextBtnText="Next" restartBtnText="Restart"><question linkID="PG1596039330426" prompt="&lt;p&gt;While paper records can last for centuries, millennia even, digital data - specifically the bits and bytes of which it is comprised - can deteriorate quickly.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;While the rate of deterioration will vary depending on the storage medium used - magnetic, optical, etc - all media decay over time (&amp;#39;bit rot&amp;#39;), introducing errors that reduce their ability to be read accurately.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;What term most accurately describes the data loss phenomenon described above?&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Question" type="Single Answer"><option linkID="PG1596039358994" text="&lt;p&gt;Data fragility&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes. Strategies to minimise &amp;#39;bit rot&amp;#39; include:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Refreshment - move data files onto new storage media well within the projected lifespan of the media.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Replication - by keeping more than one copy of a data file, in different locations, the risk of losing a readable copy over time is reduced.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;" correct="true"/><option linkID="PG1596039386850" text="&lt;p&gt;Data fertility&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option linkID="PG1596039405537" text="&lt;p&gt;Data formality&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/></question><question linkID="PG1596039223361" prompt="&lt;p&gt;The pace of technological advance has resulted in ever more obsolescence as new developments overtake and make existing technologies redundant.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;File format obscelence can occur when files created using an older version&amp;nbsp;of a software package are no longer supported following an update or release of a new version of the software. It may also be caused by software producers&amp;nbsp;no longer updating their software leading to compatibility issues with&amp;nbsp;later operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;What term most accurately describes the data loss phenomenon outlined above?&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Question" type="Single Answer"><option linkID="PG1596039253001" text="&lt;p&gt;Software adolescence&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option linkID="PG1596039281833" text="&lt;p&gt;Software opulescence&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option linkID="PG1596039290617" text="&lt;p&gt;Software obsolescence&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes. Strategies to reduce software obsolescence include:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Migration - when a new software version has become established, the data file is converted or &amp;#39;migrated&amp;#39; to the new software version or package.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Emulation - recreate the functionality of the obsolete software package on a new operating system.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Format conversion - the most pro-active method is to select a neutral or non-proprietary format that is most easily imported into a number of suitable software programs, or that is based on a universal standard.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/></question><question linkID="PG1596039443658" prompt="&lt;p&gt;The Open Archival Information Standard Reference Model (OAIS), orginally developed by space scientists, is the pre-eminent model for preservation planning and is an International Standards Organisation (ISO) standard.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;The Digital Curation Lifecycle Model is useful for mapping the planning, preservation, and curation activities associated with a digital object into a lifecycle view.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;What term most accurately describes the objectives of the models outlined above?&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Question" type="Single Answer"><option linkID="PG1596039462984" text="&lt;p&gt;Planning for data recovery&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option linkID="PG1596039479001" text="&lt;p&gt;Planning for data analysis&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option linkID="PG1596039494177" text="&lt;p&gt;Planning for data preservation&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" name="Answer" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Yes. Preservation plans should include the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;regular back up schedules (including multiple copies in multiple locations)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;strategies to prevent data loss&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;file format migration plans&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;check sums (bit integrity checking)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;version control&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;data security&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;data storage media&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;copyright and licensing&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/></question></quiz><buttonQuestion linkID="PG1311353280161" name="Time to reflect" instruction="In thinking about your planned research, consider what software dependencies you have and what risks are involved with these dependencies." prompt="Can you think of a way to reduce the risk to the longevity of your research outputs by using or saving to another format? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Can you envisage a reason you might have to migrate your work to another file format before your research is finished?" label="Check" feedback="If you are using proprietary software for your research, how likely is it that the company will change hands sometime soon? Is there an option to export a generic, non-proprietary format, such as OpenDocument Formats (ODF), .csv format for tabular data files, text, html/xml/sgml or pdf-A format for word processed files, tiff or jpeg formats for raster files etc? Should that be included in your data management plan?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Have you familiarised yourself with any discipline-specific data standards there may be in your field?" align="Left" panelWidth="Medium"/><text linkID="PG1596043776058" name="Preservation and trusted repositories"><![CDATA[<p>Depositing your research data in a data archive or data repository will facilitate its discovery and preservation. It will also ensure the long-term preservation of your data for future access by you and other researchers. While you may share your data informally by emailing it to requestors or posting it to a website, informal methods of sharing such as these will make it difficult for people to find and access your data both now and in the long-term.<br />
<br />
<b>Local institutional repositories</b><br />
<br />
Some universities have their own data repositories that offer the facility for researchers to deposit, share and licence their data resources for discovery and use by others.<br />
<br />
The University of Edinburgh hosts one such institutional repository in the form of <a href="http://datashare.is.ed.ac.uk/" target="_blank">Edinburgh DataShare</a>, set up and managed by the University&#39;s Data Library (co-authors of MANTRA).<br />
<br />
<b>National repository services</b><br />
<br />
Some of the UK research councils fund data services to curate, disseminate and preserve data created as part of their funded programmes. Examples include the Economic and Social Research Council&#39;s UK Data Service, formerly known as the Economic and Social Data Service, and the seven designated data centres of the Natural Environment Research Council.<br />
<br />
Teaching materials related to research data for use by students can be deposited in Jorum, a national repository of learning objects for UK higher and further education.</p>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1596043044988" name="Data compression" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/Compression_DigitalPreservation.png'" tip="Data compression image by J&#xF8;rgen Stamp (digitalbevaring.dk, CC-BY)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>At some point you may choose to compress your data files for the purpose of local or networked storage, transportation or transmission. This is called bit-rate reduction, which involves encoding information using fewer bits than the original representation.<br />
<br />
Zip (.zip) is a <i>de facto</i> standard compression format that is used on Windows, Macintosh, Linux and Unix platforms, though there are others, sometimes specific to a particular operating system. A self-executing zip file (.exe) should not be used if the file is to be decompressed on another operating system.<br />
<br />
Zip is a &quot;lossless&quot; type of compression, which means the file should be identical to the original once unzipped. There are also &quot;lossy&quot; types of compression associated with some multimedia file formats, which may result in some distortion or loss of quality/fidelity when played.<br />
<br />
Tar (tape archive) files are commonly used in Unix / Linux to bundle a set of files into one. Tar files may also be zipped to reduce the file size (.tar.Z or tar.gz or .tar.bz2). In Windows environments the zip file can be used for the same purpose - to bundle files together, with or without compression, or with more or less compression. Utilities for tar files in Windows also exist.<br />
<br />
Lossiness can be one trade-off of compression. Another is the processing time it takes to compress/decompress before or during use, or the amount of computing resource this takes, in the case of very large files or shared servers.</p>
]]></textGraphics><youtube linkID="PG1401450188975" name="Video: file transformation" text="Stephen Lawrie, Professor of Psychiatry at the University of Edinburgh, talks about file transformation of brain imaging data.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For video captions and high-definition (HD) video press play and activate the options (bottom, right hand side). Captions might not work when using a digital tablet. For captions and HD video you might need to watch the video directly on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oQiIZEHNf1Y&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A transcript of this video is also available on the following page." launchvideo="Launch Video"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/oQiIZEHNf1Y" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1401450524897" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[So the data we get is raw. Obviously initially the data is acquired with magnetic resonance imaging as a series of zeros and ones which a computer then applies a Fourier transformation to, which generates something like the brain images that people will be used to seeing in scientific papers or in the media. And that is only part of the data really.<br /><br />The images themselves need to undergo a number of stages, or a number of processing stages, I should say, before they can be statistically analysed by group or by individual. And that slightly differs according to the type of imaging data you're collecting, but in general principles any individual sets of scans from one scanning session for example in a particular person, need to be co-registered across time, (so then) in the same three-dimensional space, for that individual brain. <br /><br />And then they need to be co-registered, or 'normalised' is sometimes the way it's described, with reference to an average brain template, so that all the individuals of a group, for example occupy, the same (on average) three-dimensional space.<br />]]></text><text linkID="PG1590768515157" name="File format migration" textWidth="760"><![CDATA[<p>At some time during your research you may need to convert or migrate your data files from one format to another. This may be due to a new computer, new software, sharing with someone who has different software, working on a shared platform instead of your own PC, or simply in order to ensure that your data can be read and used in the future.<br />
<br />
Some lossiness - that is the loss of information and/or quality in the original data - may occur when migrating from one file format to another. It is important for you to understand what is at risk for the type of data you are working with.<br />
<br />
<b>Potential risks</b> for loss or corruption on conversion or migration to new media</p>

<ul>
	<li>Word processed files: fonts, text formatting, headers, footers, footnotes, links to other documents...</li>
	<br />
	<li>Numeric files: special characters (such as tabs), end of line returns, last characters in rows (due to row size limitations), and especially blanks used as a missing data code, last rows (due to row number limitations).</li>
	<br />
	<li>Database files: as above but also relations among items in a table and among tables.</li>
	<br />
	<li>Image files: loss of layers, colour fidelity, resolution etc.</li>
	<br />
	<li>Multimedia: as above, but attention to frame rates, sound quality, codecs and wrappers is needed.</li>
</ul>

<p>File sizes may change and even become surprisingly large.<br />
<br />
It is worth briefing yourself on the format you are converting from and to before you begin; at least look them up on the Web.<br />
<br />
Check the integrity of converted files as thoroughly as possible immediately afterwards, e.g. by counting rows and columns, testing functionality, testing export, etc. as well as simply &#39;eyeballing&#39; the data to check it looks as it should.<br />
<br />
A checksum algorithm tool can be used to compare the bits of a file copied from one medium to another, but these won&#39;t work if the file format changes, or if comparing files on different computing platforms.</p>
]]></text><morphImages linkID="PG1311678246727" name="Data transformations (1)" text="There are a number of reasons you might need to transform your data during your research project or afterwards. Unlike the earlier discussion about migrating your file format, data transformation involves computing new values from old in the actual data content.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some transformations are purely statistical, and are used to prepare the data to fit a model. An example was given earlier of one kind of transformation - logarithmic transformation to make a skewed distribution fit on a normal (bell) curve.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Of course there are implications for decisions about which form of the data to keep for the long term, which form to share with other researchers, and how to document all changes to the data. Other units in this module cover these topics." url="FileLocation + 'media/letter-fall3d-by-DaveBleasdale-on-flickr-CC-BY.jpg'" url2="FileLocation + 'media/Digital-image-by-DaveBleasdale-on-flickr-CC-BY.jpg'" zoomSpeed="3"><hotspot name="zoom region" x="0" y="0" w="100" h="100"/></morphImages><text linkID="PG1311681502496" name="Data transformations (2)"><![CDATA[In survey data collected from questionnaires, multiple choice and other kinds of responses are usually coded as numbers instead of character strings. This simple type of transformation has the advantages of easing data entry if typing in paper responses and avoiding inconsistencies (e.g. typos) in data values.<br /><br />Qualitative data, for example interview transcripts, may be transformed into quantitative data by applying textual coding and categorisation techniques. Such variables (subjectively derived from a human thought process rather than computed) are understandably described as <b>categorical</b> or <b>nominal</b>, and can have a certain range of statistical techniques applied to them. Variables measured at an <b>ordinal</b>, <b>interval</b> or <b>ratio</b> level, that is 'real' numbers where a value reflects some measurement of the concept of interest, allow for a wider range of methods of analysis.<br /><br />Another reason for data transformation may be to visualise the data effectively. A simple example is converting data where there is a numerator and a denominator, from ratios to percentages in order to display on a bar chart or pie graph. <br /><br />When preparing data for display (visualisation), questions of scale and granularity arise. For example, should a line chart have daily occurences along the Y axis, or be smoothed over (averaged) to show points by week or month? The answer depends on what is worth showing in the data. Anomalies may be smoothed over at a higher level; is this desirable, to eliminate noise, or deceptive (where anomalies may be revealing)?<br /><br />A number of techniques may be used to transform confidential or sensitive data so that they may be shared with other researchers. These include:<br /><ul><li>aggregation: "the combination of related categories, usually within a common branch of a hierarchy, to provide information at a broader level to that at which detailed observations are taken." (OECD definition) Geographical data are also often aggregated to a higher unit, where information is deemed sensitive or revealing (e.g. postcode unit to postcode sector).</li><br /><li>anonymisation: cases are stripped of revealing identifiers such as name and address. Pseudonymisation is a common technique for protecting identities in qualitative data. </li><br /><li>perturbation:  a deliberate distortion is introduced at the level of tabular data cells. Population Census data are sometimes released with perturbations as a trade-off for geographical detail.</li></ul>]]></text><gapFill linkID="PG1311685510536" name="Summary (1 of 2)" text="You have now been introduced to file formats and transformation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As a summary task please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the gaps left in the text.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hint:&lt;/b&gt; If the word you select is not the correct word you won't be able to drop it into the gap." passage="A file |format| encodes information in a computer file, enabling another program to access data within it. HTML and PDF are two examples of commonly used file formats and may be identified by the filename suffixes |.html| and |.pdf| respectively.&lt;br /&gt;Files are based on either text or |binary| encoding; the former is both machine- and human-readable and the latter only readable by means of appropriate software. Thus |text|  files are less likely to become obsolete. Examples of file name extensions for text files are .txt and |.csv|.  &lt;br /&gt;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="Well done! Please continue to the second part of the activity on the next screen." panelWidth="Large"/><gapFill linkID="PG1399047214499" name="Summary (2 of 2)" text="" passage="If you need to convert or migrate your data files from one format to another, you need to be aware of the potential risk of the loss or |corruption| of your data and take appropriate steps to avoid/minimise it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When compressing your data files for the purpose of  storage, transportation or transmission, you encode the information using fewer bits than the original representation. Commonly used compression programs are |Zip|, GNU Zip (.gzip or .tar.gz) and Stuffit.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In your research you may also use the process of data |normalisation|; two meanings of this that may be of relevance to you are |statistical| normalisation and database normalisation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You may also need to compute new values from old in your data, a process which is called data transformation, which may also be a necessary prelude to analysing your data. Three techniques which could be classified as data transformation are |aggregation| (combining data into larger units), |anonymisation| (removing information identifying human subjects) and |perturbation| (distortion).&lt;br /&gt;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="Congratulations! You have successfully completed this unit." panelWidth="Full"/><text playNarration="false" linkID="PG1376644560028" name="Next &amp; further reading"><![CDATA[<p><b>What to do next?</b>
  <br />
  <br />
  You have now completed this unit. Take a look at the &#39;Further reading&#39; where you will find a list of resources that will help you gain further understanding of file formats, data compression, normalisation and transformations.
  <br />
  <br />
  You could also start a new unit and come back to check these resources later. We recommend that you continue
  <br />
  with the <a href="../documentationmetadataandcitation">Documentation, metadata and citation</a> unit.
  <br />
  <br />
  If you prefer, you could instead go back to the <a href="http://mantra.ed.ac.uk/">MANTRA</a> home page and choose a different unit.
  <br />
  <br />
  <br />
  <b>Further reading</b>
  <br />
  <br />
  Arms, C. R, Fleischhauer, C., Murray, K. (2013). &#39;Sustainability Factors&#39; in <i>Sustainability of Digital Formats: Planning of Library of Congress Collections</i>. Library of Congress. Compilation. Last updated 20 March 2013.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/sustain/sustain.shtml" target="_blank">www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/sustain/sustain.shtml</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  DBnormalization.com. <i>Database Design Basics: Introduction</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved 4 August 2014 from <a href="http://www.dbnormalization.com/" target="_blank">http://www.dbnormalization.com</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  Etzkorn, B. (6 November 2011). <i>Data normalization and standardization</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.benetzkorn.com/2011/11/data-normalization-and-standardization/" target="_blank">www.benetzkorn.com/2011/11/data-normalization-and-standardization</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  Francois, D. (29 January 2010). <i>Data normalization for statistical analysis</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.damienfrancois.be/blog/pivot/entry.php?id=8" target="_blank">www.damienfrancois.be/blog/pivot/entry.php?id=8</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  Wise, B. (2008). <i>Database normalization and design techniques</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.barrywise.com/2008/01/database-normalization-and-design-techniques/" target="_blank"> www.barrywise.com/2008/01/database-normalization-and-design-techniques</a>
</p>
]]></text></learningObject>
