<?xml version="1.0"?>
<learningObject language="en-GB" name="Research data in context" navigation="Linear" textSize="12" displayMode="fill window" editorVersion="3" responsive="true" theme="default"><bullets linkID="PG1593001946008" name="Learning objectives" delaySecs="1" showBullets="0" showPanel="0" panelWidth="Full"><![CDATA[<p>This unit introduces you to concepts around data, what constitutes research data, and the multiple forms of data that make up the digital world.</p>
  <br />
 <p>After completing this unit you will:
</p>
<br />
<p>▪ Be able to distinguish between various types of research data.
</p>
<p>▪ Recognise the importance of managing research materials.
</p>
<p>▪ Be aware of challenges presented by data in society.
</p>
<p>▪ Understand the need for data science and data literacy.
</p>
]]></bullets><textGraphics linkID="PG1594995634590" name="Introduction" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/data_management_image.jpg'" tip="School of Architecture image by University of Edinburgh (Copyright of the University of Edinburgh)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Research data management refers to the activity of working with research data throughout the&nbsp;research process, from data collection, to data storage and backup, through to data sharing at the end of a research project.</p>

<p>Although handling research data can be challenging, managing your data effectively will not only help your research to be robust and replicable, but can help you to anticipate potential problems that can occur during the research process, and will ensure that your research meets the requirements set out by research funders and publishers.</p>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1566398570677" name="Why is&amp;nbsp;research data management important?" hidePage="false"><![CDATA[<p>There are many potential benefits to be gained from research data management, and being conscious of how you handle your data will help you to:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Comply with funder and institutional expectations and policies</li>
	<li>Ensure your data is accessible and shareable</li>
	<li>Demonstrate responsible practice</li>
	<li>Keep your research safe and secure</li>
	<li>Increase your research efficiency</li>
	<li>Improve your research integrity</li>
	<li>Make your research outputs more visible</li>
	<li>Enable collaboration</li>
</ul>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1296223358718" name="What are&amp;nbsp;data?" align="Right" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/Flickrimage_by_bionicteaching2.jpg'" tip="Data slide by bionicteaching (Flickr, CC-BY-NC 2.0) "><![CDATA[<p>So what do we mean when we talk about data and research data?</p>

<p>Data and information are closely related concepts. Data provide the foundation from which knowledge is derived, whereby data become information in the process of being analysed.</p>

<p>Data are most commonly understood at the level at which measurements were originally collected, and may be qualitative or quantitative, factual or non-factual, numerical, textual or audio-visual.</p>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1555943938260" name="What are research data?"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Research data</strong> are:</p>

<ul>
	<li>collected, observed or generated for the purpose of analysis, to produce and validate original research results.</li>
	<li>collected across a range of disciplines using a variety of research approaches and methods</li>
</ul>

<p>The word data can mean&nbsp;different things to different people in different contexts. For example, different disciplines may adopt discipline-specific language around the subject of research data.</p>

<p>Some people refer to everything digital as data. Others refer to both analogue and digital materials as data.&nbsp;For the purposes of this course, research data will refer&nbsp;to data created in a digital form (born digital) or converted to a digital form (digitised).</p>

<p>In summary, research data refers&nbsp;to whatever is necessary to verify or reproduce research findings, or to gain a richer understanding of them.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1627901099989" name="Video: Primary data versus secondary data"><![CDATA[<p><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/G8lonzDwYsQ?rel=0" width="560"></iframe></p>

<p><strong>Primary data</strong> are data that are collected for a particular purpose (e.g. to answer particular research questions). <strong>Secondary data</strong> are data collected for one purpose that are made available for use by others for a different purpose.</p>

<p>John MacInnes, Professor of Sociology at the University of Edinburgh, talks in this video about the main differences between primary data and secondary data.</p>

<p>Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch the video directly on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G8lonzDwYsQ&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNz2TSe3kG9uHd3UtsiV_t6" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p>

<p>A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1593002239520" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>The main difference between primary data that you collect yourself and secondary is generally you are much more restricted in what you can collect if you are collecting your own data is simply because of the level of resources that&#39;s available to you so<br />
<br />
I created a dataset along with some colleagues on content analysis of data on newspapers. That was relatively easy to do because this is just a question of buying newspapers and carrying out the analysis, doing the counting and so on. It didn&#39;t involve for example travelling to interview people things like that.<br />
<br />
In secondary data analysis it&#39;s possibly used techniques like computer-assisted personal interviewing whereby a hand-held computer guides interviewer through the routine of questions that can be used for different kinds of respondent on a survey.<br />
<br />
The kind of resources that can go in into the creation of secondary data are usually much larger than the level of resources that an individual researcher will have at his or her disposal in a university and some more and more quantitative research uses secondary data just because the quality of the data produced is much higher. It&#39;s based on very well drawn random samples that can take advantage of things like stratified sampling or cluster sampling to maximize the value of the data that&#39;s gathered.<br />
<br />
Cognitive testing is done of the questions used to try and make sure that questions are actually measuring what you hope they are measuring, the data is properly cleaned and now because of the technological advances in information technology of the last ten fifteen years means that centrally created data is much more easy to disseminate and get access to from individual universities that&#39;s no longer a question for example, of sending away for computer tapes and things like that. You can go on the web and download a dataset in a matter of minutes.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1627901235661" name="Video: Limitations of secondary data"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/xlQMVV7VJtA?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>John MacInnes, Professor of Sociology at the University of Edinburgh, talks in this video about the limitations of secondary data.
</p>
<p>Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch the video directly on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xlQMVV7VJtA&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNz2TSe3kG9uHd3UtsiV_t6" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.
</p>
<p>A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.
</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1329282482067" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>There are two or three limitations of secondary data but far the most import one is you don&#39;t have control over the questions that have been asked and often times the questions being asked are not quite the question you really wanted to ask. And you have to be fairly disciplined in accepting that it&#39;s important to have a clear idea of what the variables in a secondary dataset measure and the distance between that measure and what you might ideally have liked them to be measuring. And it&#39;s tempting to pretend that they&#39;re measuring what you want them to measure rather than what they actually do measure. So that&#39;s one drawback.
  <br />
  <br />
  A second drawback is, it&#39;s quite time-consuming to organise secondary data analysis in that before you get into the analysis you have to have a good knowledge of the documentation that comes with the dataset. You need to be sure that you understand how the sampling was organised. You need to be sure that you understand how the different variables in the dataset were defined and created, what was done with the missing values, what was done with don&#39;t knows, what was done with the routing of questions to different types of respondent in the survey.
  <br />
  <br />
  And quite often it takes quite a bit of time to get your head round all those details but they are important details to understand because they are fundamental to interpreting the results of any secondary data analysis that you undertake on that dataset.
</p>]]></text><text linkID="PG1627901322453" name="Video: Challenges in working with spatial data"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/FLL74eXcl8c?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Ellie Bates, a 3rd year PhD student at the time of recording, talks in this video about the challenges in working with spatial data.
</p>
<p>Her PhD thesis, titled &ldquo;Vandalism: a crime of place&rdquo;, used police crime data and focus groups with community police to explore why there are high and low levels of vandalism in different urban places.
</p>
<p>Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch the video directly on <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLL74eXcl8c&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNz2TSe3kG9uHd3UtsiV_t6" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.
</p>
<p>A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.
</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1593002327167" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>There are a number of specific challenges with working with spatial data. Some of the challenges are the sort of challenges you get with any data. Say, there are issues of data quality, issues of compatibility between datasets. But with spatial data I would say that there are particular issues, especially with the data I am working with, around scale and also around the accuracy of the data.<br />
<br />
So when I&rsquo;m talking about accuracy I am talking about how reliably certain can I be that the location of my data, the location point I&rsquo;ve got of where something&rsquo;s occurring, in this case a crime of vandalism, because that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m looking at. How reliably certain can I be that that is accurate? Has it been put in the right spot, or not. And how reliably certain do I actually need to be? Because in my research I am particularly interested in differences at a local neighbourhood level, therefore, which is perhaps one or two streets together, or a few streets together. But I don&rsquo;t need to know precisely what street corners something happens at. So, for me, I need it to be accurate enough, though I&rsquo;m pretty certain that it is happening in the right neighbourhood, or I can be certain about something about the neighbourhood that it&rsquo;s occurring in, but I don&rsquo;t necessarily need to know which house.<br />
<br />
And in terms of scale I need to think&hellip; it&rsquo;s a similar question really. It becomes, at what level I want to look at my data at. Now I actually want to look at my data at multiple scales because I don&rsquo;t really know at what level the phenomenon is occurring at, and at what level it&rsquo;s having an influence. When you actually think about what makes up a neighbourhood you could think about it being collections of houses, you could think about it being collections of streets, you could think about it being an area of town that might have a local name. And each of these things may operate at a different scale, so you need to then start thinking about well, what kind of geographic boundaries can I actually find that might express those scales? What&rsquo;s out there that I can use? And then you need to think about well, what have these boundaries can I actually get hold of, what have they been collected for?<br />
<br />
Now I&rsquo;m working in Scotland, and in Scotland there are pre-available boundaries I can use available through the UK Borders service. And there are things like wards, or what are called the statistical geographies. So things like output areas, or data zones. Output areas are the smallest level. If you are familiar with American data, they are a bit like census blocks and they are the smallest level of data at which census data [are] released and they are designed to sort of reflect groups of, I think it&rsquo;s something like between 50 and 200 people. And so they are the sort of smallest sort of unit of kind of neighbourhood I suppose that you can get data at. And they have been produced to be relatively homogenous so as to take into account of differences between local neighbourhoods, looking at various socio-demographic variables. So they are a good neighbourhood representation.<br />
<br />
Ward data on the other hand, which tend to be at a bigger scale, have been created for electoral purposes, so for the voting people. So they tend to vary a lot in size and they tend to change over time, whereas things like output areas stay stable over a long time. So they are a good dataset for me to have a look at because I&rsquo;m looking at neighbourhoods. So, in that case, there are specific challenges in saying well&hellip; at the level I can get data at, is that useful?<br />
<br />
The second challenge you run into is that if you want to compare your localised data, such as I am using, with other data, what other data can you get, at what scale? And what you invariably seem to find is that different types of socio-demographic data are released at different scales, and at different geographical units. And you need to think about what level [are those] data available at? Is it small enough for the problem that you want to look at? In my case I actually want to look at things at a very small scale and actually there&rsquo;s not that much data available at output area level. A lot of the data I&rsquo;m interested in is released at Data Zone level, so I&rsquo;ve had to look around to see well what data [are] available and what data I can use. And what data might I be able to use that I can perhaps aggregate up at different scales. Now it turns out there is not a lot of that but there [are] data around postcodes and address counts that I have been able to look at to get a sort of rough proxy of how many people have you got in an area.<br />
<br />
A further challenge I suppose, coming back to that scale issue, is what level am I going to want to look at my data at? In my case I&rsquo;m looking at crime data. I knew I wanted to look at it at multiple scales, because I was interested in what happens at different times, what happens at different scales. Do you get different patterns when you look at [these] data at different scales? So I couldn&rsquo;t be totally certain starting out that if I said, well, just give me the postcode for my data, that that would be good enough for me to be able to aggregate it to different scales. So what I wanted was point level data. So a specific challenge for me is to get data to give me the exact location of something because once I&rsquo;ve got the exact location I can then change it or aggregate it up to whatever scale I want. That gives other challenges, but that is extremely helpful to be able to start at that level. You won&rsquo;t be able to get all data at that level but if you can, and in my case I have been able to get my ground data. If you can get some level of the exact location that can be helpful too.</p>
]]></text><list linkID="PG1564142239937" name="Data as research output" text="&lt;p&gt;During a project, your research may generate different types of &lt;strong&gt;research data&lt;/strong&gt; in a variety of digital file formats, examples of which are given here. Click on each category to see examples of some corresponding data types:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" styles=""><listItem linkID="PG1564142303123" name="Text" text="&lt;p&gt;Questionnaires&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Interview transcripts&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Codebooks&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Methodologies&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Workflows&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Standard operating procedures&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Protocols&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Field notebooks&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Diaries&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data types may include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;plain text, pdf, word, html, xml&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><listItem linkID="PG1564142322585" name="Numeric" text="&lt;p&gt;Survey responses&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Medical records&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Test responses&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Spreadsheets&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Instrument measurements&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Geospatial information&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data types&amp;nbsp;may include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Stata, SPSS, Excel, GIS&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><listItem linkID="PG1564142342305" name="Multimedia" text="&lt;p&gt;Photographs&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Audio recordings&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Videos&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data types&amp;nbsp;may include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;jpeg, png, tiff, mp3, wav, mpeg, quicktime&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><listItem linkID="PG1564142373163" name="Development code" text="&lt;p&gt;Source code&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Algorithms&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Scripts&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data types may include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Python, Java, MATLAB&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><listItem linkID="PG1564142353361" name="Syntax" text="&lt;p&gt;Software-specific code files to carry out data processing steps (e.g. data preparation, linkage, statistical analysis, etc).&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data types may include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Stata, SPSS, R, MATLAB&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><listItem linkID="PG1566402678427" name="Discipline specific" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data types may include:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Flexible Image Transport System (FITS) [Astronomy]&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Crystallographic Information File (CIF) [Chemistry]&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;GRIdded Binary (GRIB) [Meteorology]&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></list><bullets linkID="PG1566402154142" name="Research records" delaySecs="1" showBullets="0" showPanel="0" panelWidth="Full"><![CDATA[<p>In addition to research data, during a research project you will also need to think about how to manage the accompanying <strong>research records</strong> - that is administrative materials and supporting documentation - both during and beyond the life of a project. The list below gives some examples of these research records:</p>

<p><br />
▪ Correspondence (electronic mail and paper-based correspondence)</p>

<p>▪ Grant applications</p>

<p>▪ Ethics applications</p>

<p>▪ Technical reports</p>

<p>▪ Technical appendices</p>

<p>▪ Research reports</p>

<p>▪ Research publications</p>

<p>▪ Signed consent forms</p>

<p>▪ Social media communications (blogs, wikis, tweets, etc.)</p>
]]></bullets><mcq playNarration="false" linkID="PG1295627235968" name="Activity 1 - Data vs record" instruction="&lt;p&gt;This activity aims to distinguish between &lt;em&gt;research data&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;research records.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" prompt="&lt;p&gt;Select all examples of research data from the following list:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Multiple Answer" align="Left" panelWidth="Medium"><option text="Nuclear magnetic resonance image (NMRI)" feedback="&lt;b&gt;Correct.&lt;/b&gt; NMRI is a medical imaging technique used in radiology to visualise detailed internal structures such as the heart, brain, muscles." correct="true"/><option text="Technical Appendix about the methods used in the project" feedback="&lt;b&gt;Incorrect.&lt;/b&gt; A technical appendix is ancillary to the research data that was created as part of the research process." correct="false"/><option text="Audio interview file" feedback="&lt;b&gt;Correct. &lt;/b&gt;An audio file is a file format for storing audio data on a computer system (in this case a file containing a recording of a person or persons being interviewed as part of a qualitative study)." correct="true"/><option text="Thin layer chromatogram" feedback="&lt;b&gt;Correct.&lt;/b&gt; Thin layer chromatogram (TLC) is the result of a widely employed laboratory technique to separate mixtures using a thin absorbent layer." correct="true"/><option text="Email correspondence about the project" feedback="&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Incorrect.&lt;/b&gt; Primarily email refers to a means of exchanging information. Such information may be about the research process, or about research data, but usually does not represent the actual research data.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;It is however feasible that the use of email as a communications medium could in itself be the research object for analysis in social science research.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" correct="false"/><option text="Georeferenced satellite image" feedback="&lt;b&gt;Correct.&lt;/b&gt; This is a digitally created image of a part of the earth created by a satellite whose location has been assigned in terms of a map projection or coordinate system." correct="true"/></mcq><textGraphics linkID="PG1594996098739" name="Classification of research data" align="Right" imagesize="actual size" url="FileLocation + 'media/FLICKR_by_Conor_Lawless.PNG'" tip="Mutation Rate image by Conor Lawless (FLICKR, CC-BY 2.0)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>As we have seen, research data can be generated for different purposes and through different processes in a multitude of digital formats.</p>

<p>The following classification,&nbsp;compiled by the Research Information Network, gives one&nbsp;way to categorise research data according to the different contexts in which they are created:</p>

<p><strong>Observational</strong>: data captured in real time, usually unique and irreplaceable.</p>

<p><strong>Experimental</strong>: data from experimental results, e.g. from lab equipment, often reproducible, but can be expensive.</p>

<p><strong>Simulation</strong>: data generated from test models where model and metadata may be more important than output data from the model.</p>

<p><strong>Derived or compiled</strong>: resulting from processing or combining &#39;raw&#39; data, often reproducible but expensive.</p>

<p><strong>Reference or canonical</strong>: a (static or organic) conglomeration or collection of smaller (peer reviewed) datasets, most probably published and curated.</p>
]]></textGraphics><buttonQuestion linkID="PG1314895319312" name="Activity 2 - Classify your own data" instruction="&lt;p&gt;Depending upon the kind of research or analysis you do, you may create a range of research data. This&amp;nbsp;data&amp;nbsp;may be of only one type, or it may include several different classes of data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" prompt="&lt;p&gt;Think about the different types of data your research will produce, and consider which of the following classifications apply to your own research data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observational&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;strong&gt;Simulation &lt;/strong&gt;or &lt;strong&gt;model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;strong&gt;Derived &lt;/strong&gt;or &lt;strong&gt;compiled&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;strong&gt;Reference &lt;/strong&gt;or &lt;strong&gt;canonical&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;Check &lt;/strong&gt;button for examples of how&amp;nbsp;these may be used to classify different types of data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" label="Check" feedback="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observational data&lt;/strong&gt; are captured in real time, usually unique and irreplaceable.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;e.g. brain images, survey data.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;strong&gt;Experimental data&lt;/strong&gt; are from lab equipment, often reproducible, but can be expensive.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;e.g. chromatograms, microassays.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;strong&gt;Simulation &lt;/strong&gt;or &lt;strong&gt;model data&lt;/strong&gt; are generated from test models where model and metadata may be more important than output data from the model.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;e.g. economic or climate models.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;strong&gt;Derived &lt;/strong&gt;or &lt;strong&gt;compiled data&lt;/strong&gt; result from processing or combining &amp;#39;raw&amp;#39; data, often reproducible but expensive.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;e.g. compiled databases, text mining.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;  &lt;strong&gt;Reference &lt;/strong&gt;or &lt;strong&gt;canonical data&lt;/strong&gt; are a (static or organic) conglomeration or collection of smaller (peer reviewed) datasets, most probably published and curated.&#10;  &lt;br /&gt;&#10;e.g. gene databanks, crystallographic databases.&#10;&lt;/p&gt;" align="Left" panelWidth="Medium"/><textGraphics linkID="PG1594995823571" name="The Three Vs" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/big data.JPG'" tip="Big Data image by BBVAtech (CC-BY 2.0)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>As far back as 2001, research report analyst Doug Laney outlined the coming challenges and opportunities in data growth in terms of data <strong>volume</strong>, <strong>velocity </strong>and <strong>variety</strong> (summarised in the image to the right).
</p>
<p>Commonly referred to as the &quot;three V&#39;s&quot; of big data, further terms to describe the issues and challenges of working with large and complex data have been proposed. For example, data <strong>veracity&nbsp;</strong>refers to issues surrounding data trustworthiness and reliability, while other terms include data <strong>volatility</strong>, <strong>visualization </strong>and <strong>value </strong>(see Further reading, &quot;The 10 Vs of Big Data&quot;)<strong>.</strong>
</p>
]]></textGraphics><nav linkID="PG1563981816747" name="Data in society" text="&lt;p&gt;Big data goes beyond traditionally structured data to include semi-structured and&amp;nbsp;unstructured information from an ever expanding range of sources.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Examples of such data include:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Social media data&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Administrative data&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Corporate data&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Transactional data&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Sensor data&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Click on each button for more details.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Button" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1563981816771" name="&lt;strong&gt;Social media data&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social media&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/strong&gt; (or simply social data)&amp;nbsp;are&amp;nbsp;generated by the online activity of&amp;nbsp;users of social media platforms. This may include:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Content (text, images, videos, etc)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Activity (posts, shares, comments, follows, etc)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Metadata (biographical information, location, etc)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Social data may be used for various purposes, including:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Curating content&amp;nbsp;shown to users&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Promoting stories or events&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Targeting advertising based on user characteristics&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Some social media platforms provide &lt;b&gt;application programming interfaces&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;(APIs) which allow&amp;nbsp;data to be downloaded for the purpose of analysis. However, the scale and complexity of social data often requires the application of very advanced data analysis techniques (e.g. machine learning, data mining, etc).&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1563981816774" name="&lt;strong&gt;Administrative data&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Administrative data&lt;/strong&gt; are routinely collected and processed in the day-to-day administration of public services. These data include:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Social security payment records&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Educational attainment records&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Health records&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Court records&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Tax records&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the primary use of data in the delivery of public services, anonymised administrative data are routinely published, for example aggregated national statistics.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Where access to administrative data for research purposes has been agreed, access to anonymised and linked data is commonly conditional on data being accessed only within a secure setting, with accompanying procedures for statistical disclosure control.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;For example, Administrative Data Research UK&amp;nbsp;(ADR UK) will facilitate access to and the analysis of administrative data for research, with centres in Scotland, Wales, and Northern Ireland.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" url="Select Media" tip="Enter a Description for Accessibility" align="Top"/><navPage linkID="PG1563981816779" name="&lt;strong&gt;Corporate data&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate data&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;are collected for and used in the day-to-day planning, administration and operation of a&amp;nbsp;business or organisation. These data may include information on the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Finances&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Taxes&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Employees&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Customers&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Suppliers&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Information about the business itself&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Corporate data are confidential, and may include both&amp;nbsp;personal data and&amp;nbsp;commercially sensitive information. The use of corporate data for research is often limited to comparative analysis of aggregate data from different companies,&amp;nbsp;or will be dependent on restrictive access conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1563981816794" name="&lt;strong&gt;Transactional data&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transactional data&lt;/strong&gt; record the changes to a record resulting from a transaction. For example, logs generated by electronic systems utilized by a business, organisation or service to track who we are, what we do, and when - and potentially where &amp;ndash; we do it.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Transactional data support the logistics of business operations, from stock management (e.g. stock availability, forecast and replenishment), delivery (e.g. tracking a parcel), and provision of associated services, such as loyalty cards (e.g. targeted offers to customers based on shopping behaviour).&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Transactional data may contain detailed personal information about individuals, their activities, and the internal procedures of businesses. As such, analysis of transactional data for research purposes is likely to be restrictive.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1563981816802" name="&lt;strong&gt;Sensor data&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensor data&lt;/strong&gt; are generated by an increasing array of technological devices which can be used to measure different elements of the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Modern technology such as smart phones, video game&amp;nbsp;consoles, fitness trackers, navigation devices, and other devices include sensors able to measure,&amp;nbsp;process and respond to:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Sound (e.g. voice activation)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Motion (e.g. pedometer)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Orientation (e.g. x, y, z axis changes)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Location (e.g. GPS tracking)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Environmental conditions (e.g. light, temperature)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Health factors (e.g. heart rate, blood glucose level)&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Sensor data are&amp;nbsp;used routinely in traditional research (e.g. scientific experiments and medical research).&amp;nbsp;However, the rise of the &amp;#39;internet of things&amp;#39;,&amp;nbsp;whereby sensor-enabled devices become able to transfer&amp;nbsp;data and interact with other systems autonomously, has seen &amp;#39;sensor data analytics&amp;#39; develop&amp;nbsp;as a key data challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nav><textGraphics linkID="PG1594997114737" name="Data Science" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/data_science_venn_2019_v2.PNG'" tip="Data science Venn diagram image by MANTRA team (CC-BY 4.0)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>The label&nbsp;<strong>Data Science</strong>&nbsp;reflects the combination of skills and knowledge which are necessary to effectively analyse and&nbsp;process increasingly large and complex data sources.</p>

<p>The three dimensions of data science (shown in the Venn diagram to the right) are:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Domain knowledge</li>
	<li>Coding skills</li>
	<li>Maths and statistics</li>
</ul>

<p>The need for this&nbsp;combination of skills will often involve individuals from different fields, with different skill sets and knowledge, working&nbsp;together collaboratively.</p>
]]></textGraphics><text linkID="PG1627901365035" name="Video: Machine learning"><![CDATA[<p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/f_uwKZIAeM0" width="560"></iframe></p>

<p>The combination of increased computer power, advanced data science skills, and the need to process exponentially larger amounts of data has seen the application of <strong>machine learning</strong> play an increasing role in modern life.</p>

<p><em>&quot;Machine learning is a method of data analysis that automates analytical model building. It is a branch of artificial intelligence based on the idea that systems can learn from data, identify patterns and make decisions with minimal human intervention&quot;</em> (&#39;Machine Learning: What it is and why it matters&#39;, SAS [web site], https://www.sas.com/en_gb/insights/analytics/machine-learning.html, accessed 23 August 2019).</p>

<p>The video above by OxfordSparks provides a short and simple introduction to the concept of machine learning. Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &#39;cog&#39; button below the video). You can also watch the video directly on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f_uwKZIAeM0&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNz2TSe3kG9uHd3UtsiV_t6" target="_blank">YouTube</a>.</p>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1594996839466" name="Data literacy and skills" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/PD_OLD_8.jpg'" tip="Academic Registry image by Paul Dodds (Copyright of the University of Edinburgh)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p><em>&quot;Data literacy is the ability to read, work with, analyze, and argue with data. Much like literacy as a general concept, data literacy focuses on the competencies involved in working with data&quot;</em> (&#39;Data Literacy&#39;, Wikipedia, https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_literacy, accessed&nbsp;23 August 2019).</p>

<p>In the modern information society, where the understanding of what data are and how they can be used are constantly evolving, it is important to ensure that you have the skills necessary to work effectively in the digital environment.</p>

<p>To find out more about the availability of training to develop your own data literacy skills, contact library services at your own institution for more information.</p>
]]></textGraphics><gapFill playNarration="false" linkID="PG1564134430882" name="Summary" text="You have now been introduced to the concept of research data,  what constitutes research data, and how it differs from other types of information. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As a summary task please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the grey gaps left in the text.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hint:&lt;/b&gt; If the word you select is not the correct word you won't be able to drop it into the gap.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;" passage="&lt;p&gt;Research data are collected, observed, or created, for the purposes of analysis to produce and |validate| original research results.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;Big Data can be categorised by the three Vs: velocity, variety and |volume|.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The three dimensions of data science&amp;nbsp;are: |domain| knowledge, coding skills, maths and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;To find out about training to develop your own data literacy&amp;nbsp;skills, contact |library services| for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! You have successfully completed this unit.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" panelWidth="Large"/><text linkID="PG1566565516388" name="Next &amp; further reading"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What to do next?</strong></p>

<p>You have now completed this unit. To gain further understanding of what constitutes research data and for more information on the topics covered in this module we suggest that you consult the &#39;Further reading&#39; resources below.</p>

<p>You could also start a new unit and come back to check these resources later. We recommend that you continue with the <a href="../datamanagementplanning/">Data management planning</a> unit.</p>

<p>If you prefer, you could instead go back to the <a href="https://mantra.ed.ac.uk/">MANTRA</a> home page and choose a different unit.</p>

<p><br />
<strong>Further reading</strong></p>

<p>Australian Research Data Commons. About data: What to consider when using data management frameworks and strategies. Retrieved 1st June 2022 from:<br />
<a href="https://ardc.edu.au/resources/aboutdata/" target="_blank">https://ardc.edu.au/resources/aboutdata/</a>.</p>

<p>Firican, G. (2017) The 10 Vs of Big Data [web page]. Retrieved 23 August 2022 from:<br />
<a href="https://tdwi.org/articles/2017/02/08/10-vs-of-big-data.aspx" target="_blank">https://tdwi.org/articles/2017/02/08/10-vs-of-big-data.aspx</a>.</p>

<p>Fix, Blair. (2019). Ten Tips For Doing Open Science. Retrieved 1st June 2022 from:<br />
<a href="https://economicsfromthetopdown.com/2019/11/28/ten-tips-for-doing-open-science/" target="_blank">https://economicsfromthetopdown.com/2019/11/28/ten-tips-for-doing-open-science/</a>.</p>

<p>Garber, A.M. (2019). Data Science: What the Educated Citizen Needs to Know. Harvard Data Science Review.<br />
<a href="https://doi.org/10.1162/99608f92.88ba42cb" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1162/99608f92.88ba42cb</a>.</p>

<p>Jisc. (2018). Research Data Management Toolkit. Retrieved 1st June 2022 from:<br />
<a href="https://www.jisc.ac.uk/guides/rdm-toolkit " target="_blank">https://www.jisc.ac.uk/guides/rdm-toolkit </a>.</p>

<p>Nature. (2016). <em>1,500 scientists lift the lid on reproducibility</em>.<br />
<a href="https://www.nature.com/news/1-500-scientists-lift-the-lid-on-reproducibility-1.19970" target="_blank">https://www.nature.com/news/1-500-scientists-lift-the-lid-on-reproducibility-1.19970</a>.</p>

<p>Sonkar, S. (2020). What is Big Data? A Quick Introduction for Analytics and Data Engineering Beginners. Retrieved 1st June 2022 from:<br />
<a href="https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2020/11/what-is-big-data-a-quick-introduction-for-analytics-and-data-engineering-beginners/" target="_blank">https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/blog/2020/11/what-is-big-data-a-quick-introduction-for-analytics-and-data-engineering-beginners/</a>.</p>

<p>Strasser C., Cook R., Michener W., Budden A. Primer on Data Management: What you always wanted to know (PDF, 206KB). Retrieved 1 August 2022&nbsp;from:<br />
<a href="https://old.dataone.org/sites/all/documents/DataONE_BP_Primer_020212.pdf" target="_blank">https://old.dataone.org/sites/all/documents/DataONE_BP_Primer_020212.pdf</a></p>

<p>UK Data Service. The importance of managing and sharing data. Retrieved 1st June 2022 from:<br />
<a href="https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/learning-hub/research-data-management/" target="_blank">https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/learning-hub/research-data-management/</a>.</p>

<p>UK Reproducibility Network (UKRN). (2021). Data Sharing - a UKRN animated primer [video]. Available from:<br />
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wjWAUrvA6c4" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wjWAUrvA6c4</a>.</p>

<p>University of Edinburgh. (2021). Research Data Management Policy. Retrieved 1st June 2022 from:<br />
<a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/information-services/about/policies-and-regulations/research-data-policy" target="_blank">https://www.ed.ac.uk/information-services/about/policies-and-regulations/research-data-policy</a>.</p>
]]></text></learningObject>
