<?xml version="1.0"?>
<learningObject language="en-GB" name="Keeping research data safe" navigation="Linear" textSize="12" displayMode="fill window" editorVersion="3" responsive="true"><bullets linkID="PG1606148591489" name="Learning objectives" delaySecs="1" showBullets="0" showPanel="0" panelWidth="Full"><![CDATA[<p>This unit introduces you to issues involved in storing, securing and backing up your research data.</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p>After completing this unit you will:</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p>▪ know how to protect your data by taking adequate precautions.</p>

<p>▪ be aware of the options available to you to safely store your data.</p>

<p>▪ recognise the importance of data backups.</p>

<p>▪ understand password safety guidelines.</p>

<p>▪ know how to encrypt and destroy sensitive data when required.</p>
]]></bullets><textGraphics linkID="PG1641922834634" name="Introduction" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/archive-1850170_960_720.jpg'" tip="'Archive' image by Pexels (Pixabay, https://pixabay.com/service/license/)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Data are at the centre of all research and it is essential that you take good care of research data to ensure that you do not lose all your hard work should something unexpected happens.&nbsp;Remember, recovering lost data is likely to take time, could be costly, and in the worst case scenario your data may even be impossible to recover.</p>

<p>To avoid such an unfortunate scenario, it is essential that your research&nbsp;data are stored suitably, are routinely backed up, and are appropriately safeguarded to ensure they&nbsp;remain protected and accessible to you as long as you need them to be.</p>
]]></textGraphics><table linkID="PG1634045184512" name="Classify your data" text="&lt;p&gt;All research data&amp;nbsp;should be managed&amp;nbsp;appropriately to ensure that they&amp;nbsp;can only be accessed by the right people, and&amp;nbsp;this is particularly important when working with sensitive data. To protect data effectively&amp;nbsp;you need to consider how the different types of data that you generate during your research project need to be managed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Using a data classification scheme will help you to determine how different types of data should be managed, according to the level of risk and impact&amp;nbsp;of the data being lost, leaked or misused.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Refer to your own institution&amp;rsquo;s data classification scheme in the first instance.&amp;nbsp;For example, the data classification scheme shown here refers to the University of Edinburgh&amp;#39;s three-level classification scheme which provides guidance on the management of different types of information and data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="left"><tableData linkID="PG1634045184522" name="Example Data Classification Scheme" data="Classification Level &amp; Definition|Data Examples|Security Control Examples||1: Unrestricted -- Data that can be safely made public.|Anonymous data. Open or published data.|Register of where data are published and when they are updated||2: Restricted ----- Data for a specific audience, where wider release may cause harm.|Personally identifiable information. Commercially sensitive information.|Encrypt and apply access controls. Secure paper documents when not in use.||3: Confidential --- Highly sensitive data, where release would cause significant harm.|Special category data (e.g. health data). Items covered by non-disclosure agreement. Legally privileged documents.|Encrypt and apply strict access controls. Use enterprise IT systems. Two factor authentication." size="medium" borders="none" header="header" shadeHeader="true" shade="true"/></table><youtube linkID="PG1636389806560" name="Video: Secure storage" text="&lt;p&gt;You are likely to have a number of different storage options&amp;nbsp;available to you (e.g. file servers, cloud storage, etc.) and you will need to evaluate the risks and benefits of each to&amp;nbsp;determine the most appropriate method to safeguard your data and minimise data loss.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This includes thinking about how your data will be backed up to ensure that they&amp;nbsp;can be&amp;nbsp;recovered&amp;nbsp;should anything unfortunate happen.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Managing access to your data is an important aspect of data security to ensure your data are&amp;nbsp;protected and accessible only to those who need and are authorised to access them. Implementing strict authentication and authorization measures such as strong passwords, encryption for sensitive data, and secure transfer mechanisms, will help to provide secure access to your data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This short video by LSI Storage provides a visual introduction to the key challenges to data security and ways to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"><![CDATA[<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ylkg7-JOYX8" title="YouTube video player" width="560">
  </iframe>]]></youtube><textGraphics linkID="PG1639475851163" name="Institutional network&amp;nbsp;drives" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/network-drive.PNG'" tip="'Network drives example' image by MANTRA team (CC-BY)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>It is common for your own institution to provide access to network storage, allowing you to store and access your research data while connected to your&nbsp;institutional network.</p>

<p>Institutional network drives are managed by your institution&nbsp;to be secure and protect&nbsp;against different data loss scenarios. For example, network storage will be routinely backed up&nbsp;and provide&nbsp;account authentication systems to protect&nbsp;against&nbsp;unauthorised access.</p>

<p>To protect your research data <strong>it is highly recommended that you store your research data on a centrally-managed&nbsp;network&nbsp;drive</strong>. This will ensure that your data are:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Stored in a single place and backed up regularly</li>
	<li>Available to you as and when required, for example via VPN when working off-site</li>
	<li>Stored securely minimising the risk of loss, theft or unauthorised use</li>
</ul>

<p>Check with your local IT support for information about your&nbsp;institution&#39;s network storage options and backup schedule.</p>
]]></textGraphics><buttonQuestion linkID="PG1297949388802" name="Activity: storage" instruction="Take a couple of minutes to think about the question given on the right and make a note of your answer.  Then, &lt;b&gt;click&lt;/b&gt; on the 'Check' button to compare your notes with the feedback provided." prompt="&lt;p&gt;What do you think would be the advantages of storing your data on institutional, centrally-managed networked drives?&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" label="Check" feedback="If you store your data on the university networked drives your data will be stored in a single place and backed up regularly.  The risk of loss, theft or unauthorised use will be minimised as the data will be stored securely on these networked drives. Your data will also be available to you as and when required. Therefore, you should keep at least one copy of your master data files on the networked services.&lt;br /&gt;" align="Left" panelWidth="Medium" hidePage="false"/><textGraphics linkID="PG1639476727482" name="Cloud storage" align="Right" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/cloud_storage4_image.PNG'" tip="'Cloud storage' image by MANTRA team, CC-BY" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Cloud storage solutions such as Google Drive, Dropbox, Microsoft OneDrive and iCloud are widely available and easy to use, giving&nbsp;you the ability to upload, access and share files remotely, anywhere that has an internet connection.</p>

<p>In the event of a local hard drive failure or other hardware malfunction, you can access the most recently uploaded version of your files on the cloud, providing a backup solution for your local storage on physical drives. However, if you are on a slow network or somewhere without internet you may have issues accessing data hosted in the cloud.</p>

<p>Some institutions have moved to cloud providers to&nbsp;provide institutional storage, in place of conventional network storage. Because a contract exists between the institution and the cloud provider these can be used in the same way as centrally-managed networked drives.</p>

<p>However, be aware that cloud storage provided under contract differs&nbsp;from the free cloud storage services offered by cloud providers. Caution should therefore be used when storing research data in the cloud using free services where it may be difficult to determine or control how data stored in the cloud are processed.</p>

<p>This is particularly important when data are sensitive, and&nbsp;you should confirm that your use of cloud services to store data fully complies with applicable data protection laws before storing sensitive data in the cloud.</p>
]]></textGraphics><textGraphics linkID="PG1639476792859" name="Portable storage" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/Portable_storage_image.jpg'" tip="'Portable storage' image by MANTRA team (CC BY 4.0)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>The increasing amount of digital information we access, generate and consume means it has become increasingly commonplace to rely on portable storage solutions to store, back up and transport our data. These can be an attractive option for storing your research data due to their low cost, large storage capacities and portability.</p>

<p>However, it is important to recognise the potential risks involved with storing important data on external HDD/SSD drives and flash memory devices such as USB pen drives and SD/microSD memory cards.</p>

<p>Although convenient they pose a significant security risk due to their portability, and are easily damaged, lost, or stolen, leading to potential data loss. Further, all storage devices will eventually fail, and sooner rather than later if they are not stored and used properly.</p>
]]></textGraphics><nav linkID="PG1633942055373" name="Storage considerations" text="&lt;p&gt;While you should ensure your research data are kept on a backed up network drive, there may be situations where this may not be possible. For example, if you are conducting fieldwork or are otherwise unable to&amp;nbsp;access your institutional network.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;In such cases, there are a number of things to consider before using&amp;nbsp;cloud storage or portable storage solutions to store your research data. Click the tabs in the panel on the right for more details.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Tab" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}" hidePage="false"><navPage linkID="PG1633942132434" name="&lt;strong&gt;Cloud storage&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Before using cloud storage you should think carefully about whether the cloud service you plan to use meets your requirements. Consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;What measures are there to prevent loss of, or damage to, the data?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Can the data be easily extracted from the cloud service?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;If your data are sensitive,&amp;nbsp;also consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Can the data be verifiably deleted from the cloud service?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Are the data secured against unauthorised access and are all accesses audited?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Does the cloud service conform&amp;nbsp;to recognised data management/security standards, e.g. ISO 27001 or 27002?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Whose law applies to the cloud service provider?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Whose law applies to the contract between you and the cloud service provider?&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;(From https://www.jisc.ac.uk/guides/data-protection-and-research-data/security-of-research-data).&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1633942109649" name="&lt;strong&gt;Portable storage&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;If you choose to use portable devices (for example, for working data or to backup data held elsewhere), consider the following:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;Don&amp;#39;t keep the only copy of your data on a single&amp;nbsp;portable device - if your data aren&amp;#39;t backed up on a network drive then follow the 3-2-1 rule described on the next page.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;Choose high quality products from reputable manufacturers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;Follow the instructions provided by the manufacturer for care and handling, including environmental conditions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;Regularly check the media to make sure that they are not failing, and periodically &amp;#39;refresh&amp;#39; the data (that is, copy to a new drive/device).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;Ensure that any private or confidential data is encrypted.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/></nav><youtube linkID="PG1642170900140" name="Video:&amp;nbsp;The importance of backups" text="&lt;p&gt;Keeping backups is probably the most important data management task and will help protect against accidental or malicious data loss due to:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;human error&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;hardware failure&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;software or media faults&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;virus infection or malicious hacking&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;power failure&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Where possible, always store&amp;nbsp;your data on networked drives provided and maintained by your institution&amp;rsquo;s IT staff to ensure your data are regularly backed up.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;In the&amp;nbsp;video above, Dr Lucy Kissick gives a first-hand account of the importance of backing up your data to prevent the worst from happening.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"><![CDATA[<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6FWWMttBrc" title="YouTube video player" width="560">
  </iframe>]]></youtube><youtube linkID="PG1642169611683" name="Video: Backing up data" text="&lt;p&gt;If data cannot be stored on a centrally managed drive then you should follow the &lt;strong&gt;3-2-1 rule &lt;/strong&gt;to back up your data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;This means you should keep at least &lt;strong&gt;3 copies of your data&lt;/strong&gt; on at least &lt;strong&gt;2 different media&lt;/strong&gt;, with at least &lt;strong&gt;1 copy held off-site&lt;/strong&gt;, and check regularly that they work properly. This ensures that in a disaster scenario - a hard drive fails, your laptop is stolen, or your lab burns down - you have a relatively recent backup available to recover your most important data and files.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;In this video Richard Rodger, Professor of Economic and Social History at the University of Edinburgh, talks about the methods he uses to ensure his research data are backed up effectively. Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &amp;#39;cog&amp;#39; button below the video). You can also watch the video directly on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jX-XNo8KbOo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jX-XNo8KbOo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1642172145245" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>Of course when I spend all this time collecting and managing data I&#39;m also paranoid about protecting it and ensuring that I can retrieve it and that the storage is safe and retrievable should there be a systems failure or a problem with my machine or if somebody just steals my machine.</p>

<p>And I do that in a variety of ways:</p>

<p>I use the university&#39;s backup facility and store material on my own storage space within the university&#39;s systems, and that&#39;s very important. I do that routinely.</p>

<p>I have an external hard disk which I back up on a regular basis. I have something which people may be familiar with, called Time Machine, which does this for Mac, and does it every hour if I want it to do that. In point of fact I usually do it every day or two, so I use that as a means of backing up my data.</p>

<p>And I have a further additional hard disk which I also use when I&#39;m perhaps away from home. So I&#39;m in the field, I&#39;ve got a little external drive and I back up onto that so that I make absolutely sure that there are ways that I can retrieve that information should any of these systems go down.</p>

<p>What I don&#39;t do is leave it on memory sticks or things of this kind which seem to me an extremely hazardous way of keeping material. But I have some students who do that despite my admonition!</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1297426795860" name="Backup strategy"><![CDATA[<p>When backing up your research data following the 3-2-1 rule,&nbsp;remember that your retrieved data will only be as up-to-date as your most recent backup if you need to use it for recovery purposes.&nbsp;Defining and sticking to a sensible backup strategy is therefore essential to ensure that you minimise the amount of data or work lost&nbsp;should something unfortunate happen.</p>

<p>When considering your backup strategy, think through the following:</p>

<ul>
	<li>How will you back up your data?</li>
	<li>How often will you make full backups (backing all your data) and incremental backups (backing up only the data and files that have changed since the previous backup)?</li>
	<li>How long will backups be stored? It is important to understand the back-up schedule and retention policies of any centralised backup services. For example, under the Grandfather-Father-Son rotation scheme, snapshots are taken at specified intervals, such as daily, weekly or monthly.</li>
	<li>How much storage space will be required to maintain this backup schedule?&nbsp;Will multiple storage devices be needed to successfully backup all your data?</li>
	<li>How will you keep track of different versions of data, especially if backing-up to multiple devices? If using versioning software, which software will you use (e.g. Tortoise, Subversion)?</li>
	<li>If the data are sensitive, how will they be stored securely and appropriately, and how will you manage the secure deletion or destruction of data if required (e.g. at the end of your research)?</li>
	<li>What backup services are available that meet these needs and, if none, what alternatives are available?</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Important!</strong> To ensure that your backup system is working properly, you should regularly test it by restoring your data files from your backups to check that you can read them.</p>
]]></text><buttonQuestion linkID="PG1640000276085" name="Activity: data loss" instruction="Take a couple of minutes to read the scenario given on the right and try to guess how the story ends.  Then, &lt;b&gt;click&lt;/b&gt; on the 'Answer' button to compare notes with the answer provided." prompt="&lt;p&gt;One of the schools at the University of Edinburgh had worked for over a decade in collaboration with foreign partners in creating some strategic maps. Throughout the research all the data including the maps were stored on CDs that were kept on the shelves in a secure room. Years later another piece of research was to be based on the results of this research and the researchers asked for access to the data stored on the CDs.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;Do you think the researchers managed to gain access to the data?&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&lt;br /&gt;&#10;If your answer is &amp;quot;Yes&amp;quot;, how did they manage to get hold of the data?&lt;br /&gt;&#10;If your answer is &amp;quot;No&amp;quot;, why couldn&amp;#39;t they gain access to the data?&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" label="Answer" feedback="Unfortunately they couldn't gain access to the data because the CDs had been incorrectly stored in too much light and had faded over the years so that the data on them could no longer be read. All the effort and time that have gone into the research over the years have been wasted by not putting simple precautions in place at the begining of the research. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The moral of this story is that data should never be stored only on CDs/DVDs in the long term, and they in turn must be stored properly. The master copy should always be stored on networked drives, and more importantly, the backups should regularly be restored to see if the data is retrievable at any time." align="Left" panelWidth="Medium"/><nav linkID="PG1639478027190" name="Strong passwords" text="&lt;p&gt;It is common sense to take steps to ensure that your research data are protected to prevent unauthorised access.&amp;nbsp;A key aspect&amp;nbsp;of data security is choosing suitably strong passwords. However, due to the increasing number of accounts, login details and passwords we need to manage on a day-to-day basis it can be easy to&amp;nbsp;become careless&amp;nbsp;and adopt bad practices when creating&amp;nbsp;passwords.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;The slides&amp;nbsp;on the right give guidance and tips on choosing strong passwords. Click the right arrow to see the next slide.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Slide" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1639478131948" name="&lt;strong&gt;Tips for strong&amp;nbsp;passwords&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;For services you use less often, find a way to manage those passwords that works for you so that you can look them up, or work them out when you need them.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &#x25AA; Ideally, use a mix of upper- and lower-case letters, numbers and punctuation marks&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &#x25AA; A strong password looks like a random sequence of symbols - use some non-alphabetic characters such as @#$!%+-/:?_&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &#x25AA; Use non-dictionary words&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Memorise a few strong passwords for the systems you need to keep most secure. If you are using a long password, it&amp;#39;s a good idea to use 15 characters or more.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;A very useful way to choose very strong passwords, is to use a passphrase. This is a password made up of (at least) four randomly chosen words. It is as easy to remember as four randomly chosen letters, but it results in very strong passwords.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1639478053643" name="&lt;strong&gt;Mistakes leading to weak passwords&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;Do not make these mistakes when choosing a password:&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; your username as a password (even backwards or mixed up).&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; using any name, or any word in any language.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; obvious personal information (your year of birth, phone number, national insurance number, address, etc.).&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; all digits, or just one letter.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; a real word with only one or two obvious digit substitutions, like &amp;#39;p4ssword&amp;#39; or &amp;#39;5ecret&amp;#39;.&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; fewer than eight characters (a &amp;quot;brute force&amp;quot; attack can crack 7 letters in a few minutes)&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; characters from books, films, etc. (Gandalf, Sherlock), band names, song titles etc. (no matter how obscure).&lt;br /&gt;&#10;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&#x25AA; passwords that are too easy or too difficult to type: an easy password can be guessed by anyone who sees you type it, and you will only be able to type a difficult password slowly - with the same result.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1639480397098" name="&lt;strong&gt;Password strength&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image by XKCD (https://xkcd.com/936/, CC BY-NC 2.5)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" url="FileLocation + 'media/password_strength.png'" tip="'Password strength' image by XKCD (https://xkcd.com/936/, CC BY-NC 2.5)" align="Top"/></nav><text linkID="PG1635855789597" name="Password managers"><![CDATA[<p>Choosing unique and secure passwords is only one aspect of data security, with perhaps the bigger challenge being able to securely manage a potentially overwhelming range of account logins and passwords.</p>

<p><strong>Password managers&nbsp;</strong>are tools specifically designed to simplify the process of creating, storing and managing passwords. There are a large number of options to choose between, with both free and paid for services providing varying functions to help generate passwords that are strong and secure without being unmanageable.</p>

<p>Some of the key benefits that password managers commonly provide include:</p>

<ul>
	<li>You only need to remember one password</li>
	<li>Tool accessed via an app or browser extension</li>
	<li>Synchronisation across devices</li>
	<li>Automated generation of secure passwords</li>
	<li>Encryption of stored passwords</li>
	<li>Identification of potentially non-secure and compromised passwords</li>
</ul>

<p>When choosing a password manager it is advised to review the basic features and any additional features offered to ensure the service provides the security features you need. Some of the more well known password management tools and services include LastPass, Keepass, 1Password, and Dashlane.</p>

<p>Your own institution may have a recommended password management tool. For example, the University of Edinburgh provides free access to <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/infosec/how-to-protect/lastpass" target="_blank">LastPass</a> for all staff and students.</p>
]]></text><youtube linkID="PG1642758442861" name="Video: Encrypting sensitive data" text="&lt;p&gt;Encryption is the process of converting data into an unreadable code. Only those with the relevant password or decryption key are able to open the encrypted file.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;It is recommended to &lt;strong&gt;encrypt sensitive data at all times&lt;/strong&gt;. This applies regardless of whether data are being held on local storage, on network storage, or in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Encryption will help ensure your data cannot be accessed by others should anyone attempt to access your files, for example if your laptop or other storage device were lost or stolen. As with all data, it remains essential to establish a reliable and secure procedure for backing up encrypted data and managing associated passwords.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;In the video above, PhD student Ellie Bates talks about what to consider when using encryption. Playback quality and subtitles may be selected using the options menu (click the &amp;#39;cog&amp;#39; button below the video). You can also watch the video directly on &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/UbJiCIerzys&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" align="Left" hidePage="false"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UbJiCIerzys" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1642173070811" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things, obviously, you need to consider when you are using encryption is who actually has a backup of the password you&rsquo;re using for the encryption? Because actually if you&rsquo;re the only person who knows that password, you want as few people to know that as possible. But on the other hand, if you&rsquo;re the only person who knows it, if for some reason you forget it, you&rsquo;ve got a huge problem yourself. Or if for some reason somebody has to, for an emergency purpose, access your data, it&rsquo;s very unlikely to happen, without you being available, then how would that happen? What would happen if you suddenly became very ill or something like that, and for some reason your data had to be accessed or something like that. What would you do?</p>

<p>Well, the way I&rsquo;ve got around that is that I actually have a copy of the password in an envelope, which is sealed and signed across the seal, and given to my supervisors and one supervisor keeps it in a safe. So should they absolutely have to access my data, they can&rsquo;t do it without getting special permission from IT services to get into my account, which they would get in emergency situation but not otherwise, they can access the encryption. And again, I think in my proposal I made it clear that they could have access to the data so the fact that someone else does have access to the encryption key, in this case I use an encryption password, does mean that it&rsquo;s accessible.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also quite... sort of, I haven&rsquo;t forgotten the password yet but it is quite nice for me to know that there is a spare because the encryption algorithm I use, if I forget the password I can&rsquo;t get in. So it is kind of important that there is a backup somewhere, but again you need to think very carefully about where&rsquo;s that backup going to be kept and how&rsquo;s it going to be kept secure. In my case, the supervisors know the directory it&rsquo;s in, they know the password. But the things [are], sort of, kept separately in a couple of envelopes, so that&rsquo;s the way that that can be accessed. So I have a backup plan, so if you&rsquo;re using encryption you need a backup plan for getting to that encryption. You also need a securely held copy of what password you&rsquo;re using, but you need that kept with as few people as possible, preferably one or two.</p>
]]></text><nav linkID="PG1639496581333" name="&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;Encryption software and tools&lt;/span&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;There are a number of approaches to encrypting data, and the method you use will depend on your needs whether this be encrypting a laptop or simply encrypting a file or folder.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Click on the headings in the&amp;nbsp;panel to the right to find out more about how to encrypt&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" type="Acc" nextBtnTip="Next" prevBtnTip="Previous" slideCount="Slide {i} of {n}"><navPage linkID="PG1639496602068" name="&lt;strong&gt;Encrypting computers and laptops&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Microsoft Windows&lt;/u&gt;:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BitLocker&lt;/strong&gt; provides full volume encryption for Windows machines,&amp;nbsp;and can be used to encrypt external storage devices.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;m&lt;/u&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;acOS&lt;/u&gt;:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FileVault&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;provides full disk encryption.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;line-height:normal&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;Linux&lt;/u&gt;:&amp;nbsp;encryption options will vary based on your Linux installation,&amp;nbsp;speak to your local IT support team for advice.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1639496624283" name="&lt;strong&gt;Encrypting smartphones and tablet devices&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple iPhone / iPad&lt;/strong&gt; - setting a PIN to lock the screen will immediately encrypt the device.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Android smartphones / tablets&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;- device may be encrypted by default or may need to be enabled in system settings (refer to manufacturer support).&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other devices&lt;/strong&gt;: investigate device encryption before you buy.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1639496668075" name="&lt;strong&gt;Encrypting files, folders and containers&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;ul&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encrypted files/folders&lt;/strong&gt; - tools such as 7zip (Windows) and iZip (Mac) can be used to create an encrypted archive&amp;nbsp;containing&amp;nbsp;files and/or folders.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&#9;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encrypted containers&lt;/strong&gt; - rather than encrypt individual files,&amp;nbsp;tools such as VeraCrypt (Windows/Mac) and&amp;nbsp;iZip (Mac) can be used to&amp;nbsp;create an encrypted&amp;nbsp;container - use this to&amp;nbsp;securely store&amp;nbsp;sensitive data and files.&lt;/li&gt;&#10;&lt;/ul&gt;&#10;"/><navPage linkID="PG1639496682899" name="&lt;strong&gt;Pretty Good Privacy&lt;/strong&gt;" text="&lt;p&gt;The UK Data Service recommends the use of Pretty Good Privacy (PGP) standard technology which is available as open-source versions (GnuPG), or as commercial software (PGP). Encryption with such software requires the creation of a public and private key pair and a passphrase.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;"/></nav><text linkID="PG1633104666405" name="Video:&amp;nbsp;Encrypt a portable drive with BitLocker"><![CDATA[<p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y4Iosu-Yfsw" title="YouTube video player" width="560"></iframe></p>

<p><span style="line-height:normal"><span style="line-height:normal">Before encrypting your data y</span>ou should remember the following points:</span></p>

<ul>
	<li class="CxSpMiddle"><span style="line-height:normal">Data encryption is not a substitute for other data protection controls.</span></li>
	<li class="CxSpMiddle"><span style="line-height:normal">Data encryption is reliant on the creation of a strong password.</span></li>
	<li class="CxSpMiddle"><span style="line-height:normal">If the encryption key is lost, the disk image gets corrupted, or the hard disk fails, any encrypted data will be lost.</span></li>
</ul>

<p>The video above by the UK Data Service provides a demonstration of how to use BitLocker to encrypt a portable hard drive and protect your research data files.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1640081685361" name="Additional safeguards"><![CDATA[<p>When working as part of a team or when collaborating with other institutions it may be necessary to share access to data files. This&nbsp;comes with a number of data security risks, particularly when working with sensitive data.</p>

<p>Implementing additional physical and technological safeguards such as access controls<strong>&nbsp;</strong>and&nbsp;file permissions, used in combination with encryption and strong passwords, will help to ensure that only the specified individuals who need to are able to access the files they need.</p>

<p><strong>Access controls</strong> may include either physical restrictions, such as limiting access to data from a specific location such as a safe haven, or technological controls whereby access to data requires some form of authentication. This could involve two-factor authentication which requires a combination of two elements, such as a password used in combination with a one-time passcode delivered to a mobile device, to&nbsp;provide&nbsp;an additional level of security.&nbsp;In either case, management of access is designed to prevent unauthorised access.</p>

<p><strong>File permissions</strong>&nbsp;allow restrictions to be applied to individual files, or to groups of files within a specified storage location such as an area of a shared network drive. Managing permissions provides more granular controls over who is able to create, read, update, and delete specified files. This allows collaborators to share access to data and files stored in a project folder while controlling which individuals can view and modify the different files within.</p>

<p>When working on files collaboratively or as part of a research team it may be necessary to establish&nbsp;file access protocols&nbsp;if it is important that only one user accesses data a time.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1633104985367" name="Transferring files securely"><![CDATA[<p>In addition to managing local shared access to&nbsp;your data, it may also be necessary to send data files to partners and collaborators working at other locations. Be mindful that sharing data, particularly sensitive data, between users or between institutions has the potential to result in unintended disclosure.</p>

<p>The most secure way to share files is using secure file transfer protocol (SFTP). If you have questions about using SFTP&nbsp; to transfer files then contact your local IT support team.</p>

<p>Cloud-based options such as&nbsp;Microsoft One Drive and&nbsp;SharePoint provide an alternative way to share access to files. These systems may also provide&nbsp;file permission controls to restrict access to files to designated people.&nbsp;Alternatively, your own insitution may provide a cloud-based file transfer service which may be used to transfer and share files with others. For example, the <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/information-services/computing/desktop-personal/datasync" target="_blank">University of Edinburgh&#39;s&nbsp;DataSync</a> provides a cloud-based system for sharing files.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Regardless of the method you use to transfer data, to protect your data from unauthorised access it is important to ensure sensitive data and files are encrypted before, during and after transfer.&nbsp;Encryption will ensure that your files cannot be read by anyone who does not have the password needed to decrypt the files.</p>

<p>When sharing the encryption key with another person you should ensure that you take steps to do this securely. You should not send sensitive information such as encryption keys or passwords via email. Instead, the simplest and safest method is by&nbsp;telling the person&nbsp;face-to-face or by phoning them. Speaking directly to the other person protects against the key being accidentally sent to the wrong recipient, and prevents sensitive information being stored on servers over which you have no direct control.</p>
]]></text><text linkID="PG1641554675052" name="Secure destruction"><![CDATA[<p>Data minimisation is a key principle in data protection law, relating to the amount of identifying information that you collect and hold about people. In practice this means you shouldn&#39;t collect or keep identifying information longer than is necessary.&nbsp;Once analysis of sensitive data is completed the identifiable information should be removed, either by&nbsp;<span style="line-height:normal">d<span style="line-height:normal">e-identifying the data, fully&nbsp;<span style="line-height:normal">anonymising the data,&nbsp;</span>or b</span>y securely&nbsp;destroying the data as required.&nbsp;</span><span style="line-height:normal">This applies to paper records, as well as electronic records.</span></p>

<p><span style="line-height:normal">When deleting sensitive data be aware that conventional file deletion is not enough to ensure that sensitive information cannot be recovered.&nbsp;</span><span style="line-height:normal">Deleting a file&nbsp;simply removes the pointers to the disk sectors in which the data reside and files deleted in this way can be recovered using commonly available software tools.</span></p>

<p>If you need to securely destroy data, for example where a data sharing agreement requires you to securely delete the data at the end of the project, additional steps should be taken t<span style="line-height:normal">o ensure the data cannot be recovered by any means.</span></p>

<p><span style="line-height:normal">The main options for secure destruction are:</span></p>

<ul>
	<li class="CxSpMiddle"><span style="line-height:normal"> </span><span style="line-height:normal"><strong>Software </strong>is available to help erase files from hard disks - for example, BCWipe, WipeFile, DeleteOnClick, and Eraser for Windows platforms and Permanent Eraser for MacOS platforms.</span></li>
	<li class="CxSpMiddle"><strong><span style="line-height:normal"><span style="line-height:normal"><span style="line-height:normal">Deleting the&nbsp;encryption key</span></span></span></strong><span style="line-height:normal"><span style="line-height:normal"><span style="line-height:normal">&nbsp;-&nbsp;</span></span>without the accompanying encryption key, any data stored in an encrypted container or encrypted disk cannot be recovered<span style="line-height:normal"></span>.</span><strong><span style="line-height:normal"></span></strong></li>
	<li class="CxSpMiddle"><span style="line-height:normal"><strong>Degaussing </strong>disturbs the magnetic alignment of magnetic storage media and in many cases makes newer media (such as hard drives and tapes) unusable.</span></li>
	<li class="CxSpMiddle"><span style="line-height:normal"><strong>Physical destruction</strong>, through disintegration, shredding, pulverizing or incineration.</span><span style="line-height:normal"></span><br />
	<span style="font-size:11.0pt"><span style="line-height:107%"><span calibri="" style="font-family:"></span></span></span></li>
</ul>
]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1641564834509" name="Working remotely" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/vpn-3406770_960_720.jpg'" tip="'VPN' image by kreatikar (pixabay, https://pixabay.com/service/terms/#license)" transcriptbuttonlabel="Transcript"><![CDATA[<p>When working off campus you should take extra precautions before accessing data and files held on institutional&nbsp;network storage. This is particularly important if&nbsp;you are not using a computer managed&nbsp;by your own institution.</p>

<p>If you do not have a university-managed machine you should try to use a computer that is exclusively for your own use and avoid using a shared computer. You should also ensure that any university data you access&nbsp;remains&nbsp;on university systems and storage.</p>

<p>Computer security is important because it keeps your information protected. To keep your own computer secure at all times, you should ensure you have a current operating system installed, ensure it is fully&nbsp;patched and up to date, and have suitable antivirus software installed.</p>

<p>If you are dealing with sensitive data or working from an untrusted network you should consider using your institution&#39;s VPN (virtual private network) to access&nbsp;data held on your institution&rsquo;s file servers. Check your own institution&#39;s guidelines on accessing the university network remotely&nbsp;.</p>

<p>Last but not least, you should refrain from using public networks, hotspots, conference or hotel Wi-Fi to access sensitive data as these networks do not provide adequate security and should not be trusted.</p>
]]></textGraphics><gapFill linkID="PG1642154278338" name="Summary" text="You have now been introduced to the storage, backup and security issues in data management. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As a summary task please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the gaps left in the text.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hint:&lt;/b&gt; If the word you select is not the correct word you won't be able to drop it into the gap." passage="&lt;p&gt;During your research you must ensure that your research data is stored&amp;nbsp;|securely| and is regularly |backed up|.&amp;nbsp;It is highly recommended to store your research data on your&amp;nbsp;institution&amp;#39;s |networked| drives.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Using a&amp;nbsp;password |manager| will make the process of generating and managing passwords easier.&amp;nbsp;Access controls and file |permissions| can be used to restrict who can access data and how they can be used. Two-factor |authentication| provides additional security to control access to sensitive data.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#10;&#10;&lt;p&gt;Storing sensitive data in an encrypted |container| ensures only those with the corresponding encryption |key| will be able to access the data.&lt;/p&gt;&#10;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="Congratulations! You have successfully completed this unit." panelWidth="Large"/><text linkID="PG1661181805255" name="Next &amp; further reading"><![CDATA[<p><strong>What to do next?</strong>
</p>
<p>You have now completed this unit. Take a look at the &#39;Further reading&#39; section below where you will find a list of resources that will help you gain further understanding of storage, backup and security issues.
</p>
<p>You could also start a new unit and come back to check these resources later. We recommend that you continue with the <a href="../protectingsensitivedata" target="_blank">Protecting sensitive data</a> unit.
</p>
<p>If you prefer, you can also go back to the <a href="https://mantra.ed.ac.uk/">MANTRA</a> home page and choose a different unit.
</p>
<p>
  <br />
  <strong>Further reading</strong>
</p>
<p>Abouelmehdi, K., Beni-Hessane, A. &amp; Khaloufi, H. (2018). <em>Big healthcare data: preserving security and privacy</em>. Journal of Big Data 5,1.
  <br />
  <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s40537-017-0110-7" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1186/s40537-017-0110-7</a>.
</p>
<p>Brathwaite, Shimon. (2021). <em>Why are data backups important?</em>. Last accessed October 2021 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.securitymadesimple.org/cybersecurity-blog/why-are-data-backups-important" target="_blank">https://www.securitymadesimple.org/cybersecurity-blog/why-are-data-backups-important</a>
</p>
<p>Dicks, C. (2014). <em>Video and audio recordings and 8mm films - FAQ</em>. Last updated 23 July 2020. Retrieved 24 Nov 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/conservation-institute/services/care-objects/electronic-media/video-audio-recordings-8mm-films-faq.html" target="_blank">https://www.canada.ca/en/conservation-institute/services/care-objects/electronic-media/video-audio-recordings-8mm-films-faq.html</a>
</p>
<p>Jetico. (2020).<em>Benefits of Using Container Encryption vs. File Encryption</em>. Retrieved August 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.jetico.com/blog/5-benefits-using-container-encryption-vs-file-encryption" target="_blank">https://www.jetico.com/blog/5-benefits-using-container-encryption-vs-file-encryption</a>
</p>
<p>National Cyber Security Centre. <em>Secure sanitisation of storage media</em>. Retrieved 5 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/secure-sanitisation-storage-media" target="_blank">https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/guidance/secure-sanitisation-storage-media</a>
</p>
<p>O&rsquo;Toole, E., Feeney, L., Heard, K., Naimpally, R. (2018). <em>Data Security Procedures for Researchers</em>. J-PAL North America, August 2018. Retrieved 5 May 2020 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.povertyactionlab.org/sites/default/files/documents/Data_Security_Procedures_December.pdf" target="_blank">https://www.povertyactionlab.org/sites/default/files/documents/Data_Security_Procedures_December.pdf</a>
</p>
<p>Perkel, Jeffrey M. (2019) <em>11 ways to avert a data-storage disaster</em>. Nature 568, 131-132. Retrieved January 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-019-01040-w" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-019-01040-w</a>
</p>
<p>Philips, Gavin. (2020). <em>What Is PGP? How Pretty Good Privacy Works, Explained</em>. Retrieved January 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/tag/pgp-me-pretty-good-privacy-explained/" target="_blank">https://www.makeuseof.com/tag/pgp-me-pretty-good-privacy-explained/</a>
</p>
<p>Secure Storage Services. <em>How to Reduce the Risks of a Data Security Breach While Remote Working</em>. Retrieved January 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.securestorageservices.co.uk/article/44/how-to-reduce-the-risks-of-a-data-security-breach-while-remote-working-" target="_blank">https://www.securestorageservices.co.uk/article/44/how-to-reduce-the-risks-of-a-data-security-breach-while-remote-working</a>
</p>
<p>Secure Storage Services. <em>Pros and cons of cloud storage</em>. Retrieved October 2021 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.securestorageservices.co.uk/article/11/pros-and-cons-of-cloud-storage" target="_blank">https://www.securestorageservices.co.uk/article/11/pros-and-cons-of-cloud-storage</a>
</p>
<p>Singh, Vinay. (2020). <em>Top 10 Cloud Storage &amp; File-Sharing Services for 2020</em>. Retrieved January 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://cloudacademy.com/blog/top-10-cloud-storage-file-sharing-services-for-2020/" target="_blank">https://cloudacademy.com/blog/top-10-cloud-storage-file-sharing-services-for-2020/</a>
</p>
<p>UK Data Service. <em>Store your data - Backup</em>. Retrieved January 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/learning-hub/research-data-management/store-your-data/backup/" target="_blank">https://ukdataservice.ac.uk/learning-hub/research-data-management/store-your-data/backup/</a>
</p>
<p>University of Edinburgh. <em>Information Security - Encrypting devices and documents</em>. Retrieved January 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/infosec/how-to-protect/encrypting" target="_blank">https://www.ed.ac.uk/infosec/how-to-protect/encrypting</a>
</p>
<p>Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Leiden University and the Eindhoven University of Technology. (2020). <em>Data Horror Escape Room</em>. Retrieved January 2022 from
  <br />
  <a href="https://sites.google.com/vu.nl/datahorror/home" target="_blank">https://sites.google.com/vu.nl/datahorror/home</a>
</p>
]]></text></learningObject>
