<?xml version="1.0"?>
<learningObject language="en-GB" name="Documentation, metadata, citation" navigation="Linear" textSize="12" displayMode="fill window" editorVersion="3"><bullets linkID="PG1409757374869" name="Learning objectives" delaySecs="1" showBullets="0" showPanel="0" panelWidth="Large"><![CDATA[<p>This unit introduces you to the concepts of documentation and metadata.
</p>
<br />
<p>After completing this unit you will:
</p>
<br />
<p>
  ▪ Understand why documenting your research data is important, and why documentation is important for future users of the data.
</p>
<p>
  ▪ Know why and when to use metadata.
</p>
<p>
  ▪ Understand the importance of citing data, and how to do it.
</p>
]]></bullets><text linkID="PG1296572315212" name="Why document your data?"><![CDATA[While digital data by definition are machine-readable, understanding their meaning is a job for human beings. The importance of documenting your data during the collection and analysis phase of your research cannot be overestimated, especially if your research is going to be part of the scholarly record.<br /><br /><b>Help yourself</b>:<br />You may be on intimate terms with your dataset while you are collecting and analysing it, but remembering that the variable "sglmemgp" means single member of group, or the exact procedure you used to transform or derive particular variables, could potentially become difficult months or years later.<br /><br /><b>Help others</b>:<br />There are many reasons other people may want to examine or use your data - to understand your findings, to verify your findings, to review your submitted publication, to replicate your results, to design a similar study, or even to archive your data for access and re-use by others.]]></text><youtube linkID="PG1328105936234" name="Video: documentation in secondary data analysis" text="John MacInnes, Professor of Sociology, The University of Edinburgh, talks about the importance of good documentation in secondary data analysis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For video captions and high-definition (HD) video press play and activate the options (bottom, right hand side). Captions might not work when using a digital tablet. For captions and HD video you might need to watch the video directly on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ebaiwg08CW8&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNh7m1p1IWD6gBDRk7h_Xy4&amp;index=1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A transcript of this video is also available on the following page." align="Left"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Ebaiwg08CW8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1329281850620" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[The standard of data documentation has improved tremendously over the last twenty years or so. It's now standard for funding councils or ONS or other bodies who are involved in the creation of secondary data to pay much more attention to the quality and the comprehensiveness of the data documentation that goes with it. <br /><br />So that usually the problem that you face is not so much that there's a question that you can't find an answer to in the data documentation. Rather the problem is finding whereabouts,  in what is often very voluminous data documentation, that answer may lie. So that you'll have copies of all the different questionnaires that may have been used in a study, with different kinds of questionnaires for different kinds of respondents. You’ll have information about the different routings through those questionnaires that different respondents will have gone through. You've got, for example, syntax and how new variables were derived from the original variables created from respondent answers to the questions and so on and so on. <br /><br />On top of that you've got information about the way the sample was constructed, what was done with difficult to contact, or difficult to identify, members of the sample - things like that, so that there's a lot of information to get your head around when you’re starting to do a piece of secondary data analysis.<br />]]></text><textGraphics linkID="PG1311870367422" name="Examples of data documentation" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/Edwardians-datadoc-UKDA2.png'" tip="Documentation snippet from the Edwardians, UK Data Archive"><![CDATA[Some examples of data documentation are:<br /><ul><br /><li>laboratory notebooks & experimental protocols</li><br /><li>questionnaires, codebooks, data dictionaries</li> <br /><li>software syntax and output files</li><br /><li>information about equipment settings & instrument calibration</li><br /><li>database schema</li><br /><li>methodology reports</li><br /><li>provenance information about sources of derived or digitised data</li><br /></ul><br /><br />]]></textGraphics><text playNarration="false" linkID="PG1296572670484" name="Levels of documentation"><![CDATA[Research data need to be documented at various levels:<br /><ul><br /><li><b>Project level</b>: what the study set out to do, how it contributes new knowledge to the field, what the research questions/hypotheses were, what methodologies were used, what sampling frames were used, what instruments and measures were used, etc. A complete academic thesis normally contains this information in detail, but a published article may not. If a dataset is shared, a detailed technical report will need to be included for the user to understand how the data were collected and processed. You should also provide a sample bibliographic citation to indicate how you would like secondary users of your data to cite it in any publications, etc.</li><br /><li><b>File or database level</b>: how all the files (or tables in a database) that make up the dataset relate to each other; what format they are in; whether they supercede or are superceded by previous files. A readme.txt file is the classic way of accounting for all the files and folders in a project.</li><br /><li><b>Variable or item level</b>: the key to understanding research results is knowing exactly how an object of analysis came about. Not just, for example, a variable name at the top of a spreadsheet file, but the full label explaining the meaning of that variable in terms of how it was operationalised.</li><br /></ul>]]></text><youtube linkID="PG1324065148969" name="Video: documenting research data" text="Gitit Kadar Satat, a PhD student, talks about documenting research data in social sciences.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Gitit is a 2nd year PhD student at Moray House School of Education at the University of Edinburgh.  She is researching patterns of participation by children from diverse socio-economic backgrounds in out-of-school activity and how this influences academic performance.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For video captions and high-definition (HD) video press play and activate the options (bottom, right hand &lt;br /&gt;side). Captions might not work when using a digital tablet. For captions and HD video you might need to watch the &lt;br /&gt;video directly on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KFAjAapSHQY&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNh7m1p1IWD6gBDRk7h_Xy4&amp;index=4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A transcript of this video is also available on the following page." align="Left"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/KFAjAapSHQY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1329281850620" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[There is an issue within the social sciences about replicating results of studies that are being carried out. Maybe this is wider than just the social sciences, because in research you would like to enable other researchers to understand and to follow your work, to carry out additional improvements to your work once you are done, and also to perhaps check whether what you have done is adequate and at the highest level that can be reached. And I think that nowadays, with the software that we have and with the data management tools that we have … and some of them are provided by the universities … some you can download, free sometimes even. But these tools actually provide researchers nowadays with a great opportunity to keep track of all of the procedures that they carry out through their analyses. And it is just important to know how to use them and to really use them all throughout the work in order to enable other researchers to then be able to look at your work, to check it if they would like to, and, more importantly even, to continue from the point that you reached and carry this work even further. <br /><br />And I actually spend a lot of time in order to document my work, not just because I would like to make it possible for researchers in the future to look at it and to maybe continue the thread of work that I’m carrying out, but also for my own purposes. Because, as I’m sure many of you know, doing a PhD is something that takes at least three years and it is something that evolves within time. Sometimes you would like in your second year to go back and look at things that you were doing in your first year, and to revise them or to understand what have you done. So it’s very, very important, I guess, to keep track and to always make notes of the things that you carried out of the procedures, the analytical procedures that you carried out, and you can do them with the software that [is] provided now … that [is] available nowadays. <br /><br />Also, not just to keep track of what procedure you were executing but also why have you executed this specific analytical procedure. Because when you [are] actually doing the research and you [are] very much invested in the data analysis phase, you know exactly why are you doing this. It’s very clear in your mind, it’s very vivid. You do it every day for hours a day. But, after several months, when you’ve moved on, it wouldn’t necessarily be as fresh as it was. So, sometimes you may even forget why exactly you used this method. It’s very important when you’re going back to the documentation that you yourself created, to be able to find there the reason why have you used this procedure, for what purposes, and to revise it and to understand whether this is something that you would like now to use as well, or you would like to change it, and to use other methodic or analytical procedures.<br /><br />So in a way I think this is part of doing [a] PhD, also to be responsible [for] how you documenting your own work, for yourself and for others. Specifically in my case I do invest a lot of time and energy in this part of my studies and I guess that if someone would like now to replicate my work, then all this person would have to access is the files that I created because, of course, when I first started I downloaded the data files from the archive. But then I just started to modify them in the merge files and create new variables out of the ones that were already there. So my dataset now is nowhere similar to the one that I started with. So this person who would like to replicate my work would have to get this file, which I am happy to provide of course. There’s nothing there that should be under a specific licencing – it’s all free for public and academic use. This person would also have to gain access to the syntax files that I created. Again, I don’t see this as any … there is no problem there. Someone who gets these files can immediately just run them over and have the result that I created or I produced. And, of course, the thesis itself would provide a person that would like to replicate my work with the theoretical considerations that actually are behind all of this analytical work, because of course the analytical work that I carried out is based on [a] theoretical framework. So I don’t think that just taking the dataset and the syntax and running over it would really provide you [with] much. You would also have to look at the theoretical background from which these analytical procedures were carried out or were influenced.<br />]]></text><youtube linkID="PG1401785121874" name="Video: tips on documentation" text="Professor John MacInnes shares some tips on documentation and secondary data analysis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For video captions and high-definition (HD) video press play and activate the options (bottom, right hand side). Captions might not work when using a digital tablet. For captions and HD video you might need to watch the video directly on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EIZsxT-fIiQ&amp;index=4&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNh7m1p1IWD6gBDRk7h_Xy4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A transcript of this video is also available on the following page.&lt;br /&gt;" launchvideo="Launch Video"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/EIZsxT-fIiQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1401786752016" name="Video transcript"><![CDATA[I think people often imagine secondary data analysis to be a highly planned, predictable activity. In practice it's rarely like that. It's fairly rare to plan to do something, to do it, and it works the way you wanted it to work first time. <br /><br />It's quite common (certainly the way I work) to make several errors and only realise the errors that you've made as you get the results coming back. The temptation is always to just keep on re-doing things until you've got it right and meanwhile not bother keeping a record of what you're doing; and it's at that point that you can often start to get lost.<br /><br />It's important to log what you do as you do it each step of the way. That means that you only have to retrace your steps one or two stages to recover from an error, rather than finding yourself in the position of having to start everything from scratch again because something hasn't worked out the way that you planned that it would.<br />]]></text><tabNav linkID="PG1308557022345" name="Documentation example 1: Data re-use in GeoSciences" text="A use case supplied by Dr Grant Nicoll, when he was a post-doctoral researcher in the School of GeoSciences at the University of Edinburgh.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This research involves the use of seismic data acquired by the University of Edinburgh from the British Geological Survey (and previously worked on by them) &#x2013; the current study requires these data to be interpreted in Petrel (a seismic interpretation package) to create a set of surfaces &#x2013; these will then be used to create a 3D layered grid model in MPath (a fluid flow modelling package) on which fluid flow modelling will be performed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The researcher involved has not used either software package before although some training has been provided by the University  &#x2013; a brief handover of data has also been performed by a post-doctoral researcher who has previously worked on these data in MPath &#x2013; they are about to leave the University for Canada to join the company that developed MPath.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Seismic data are loaded into Petrel and correlated with well horizon depths and well logs from oil company reports  but some horizons don&#x2019;t match up.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What information would the researcher need to fix the problem?&lt;br /&gt;" panelWidth="Medium" tabWidth="120"><nestedPage controls="Native SWF" name="Questions" text="&#x2022; Who worked on these data before and what did they do to it in terms of processing?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#x2022; Are there any records available of the processing steps undertaken &#x2013; notes, logs, workflows? The researcher needs to know who did what  and where everything (i.e. data, files, reports, workflows, etc.) can be found and that everything is up to date. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#x2022; Is there anyone else available in University of Edinburgh who has used either piece of software before to offer assistance?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#x2022; If there is a problem, how easy is it going to be to fix &#x2013; are additional resources, software, etc. likely to be required? &lt;br /&gt;" align="Top"/><nestedPage controls="Native SWF" name="Solution" text="&#x2022; Discussed the problem with the post-doc (now left for Canada) &#x2013; they hadn&#x2019;t noticed the problem and models essentially had the wrong horizon depths for the shallower surfaces.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#x2022; Managed to trace the owners of the original data in the BGS and find out how they processed the data. The original time-based data had been converted to depth-based data, but they used velocities to ensure the deeper parts of the seismic were at the correct depth (the object of BGS research) &#x2013; this meant that the data were unsuitable for the University of Edinburgh study, which was to investigate the shallower seismic.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In this case, it was relatively easy to apply an additional correction to adjust the Pliocene horizons to the correct well and log depths for the current study. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Moral of the story is &#x2013; always check where the data came from, who did what to the data, how suitable they are for the current research and if unsuitable, how easy is it to effect  a remedy!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Also, make sure that you document your own data through the course of your project so that data will be usable without any problems in future.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;" align="Top"/></tabNav><textGraphics linkID="PG1311171628143" name="Documentation example 2: Laboratory notebooks" align="Left" imagesize="auto" url="FileLocation + 'media/labnotebooks_mbrill.jpg'" tip="Enter a Tooltip"><![CDATA[<p>For laboratory researchers, laboratory notebooks are crucial components of data management.<br />
<br />
They can play an important role in supporting claims relating to intellectual property developed by University researchers, and even defending claims of scientific fraud.<br />
<br />
In less extreme circumstances, they demonstrate adherence to standards of good practice, academic and ethical integrity, and compliance with contractual provisions permitting sponsors to audit work carried out in pursuit of sponsored-research.<br />
<br />
Therefore, thorough and effective management of laboratory data and the routine documentation of all lab procedures is a highly important responsibility for all laboratory researchers.</p>

<p>The next page provides detailed information on lab notebooks provided by Wikipedia.</p>
]]></textGraphics><embedDiv linkID="PG1563801147475" name="Laboratory notebook in wikipedia" src="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lab_notebook"/><youtube linkID="PG1311170826312" name="Video: guide to keeping a lab notebook" text="This video outlines reasons for, and good practice in, keeping a lab notebook.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We have no control over video captions or video quality for this resource. This video is part of the playlist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MgVbXMD-e-w&amp;index=4&amp;list=PL2XF5RiVI7GNh7m1p1IWD6gBDRk7h_Xy4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MANTRA_Documentation and Metadata_Videos&lt;/a&gt;." align="Left"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/MgVbXMD-e-w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></youtube><text linkID="PG1296572788892" name="Metadata: 'data about data'"><![CDATA[<b>What does metadata mean</b>?<br /><br />The term metadata is commonly defined as "data about data," information that describes or contextualises the data. The difference between documentation and metadata is that the first is meant to be read by humans and the second implies computer-processing (though metadata may also be human-readable). <br /><br />Documentation is sometimes considered a form of metadata, because it is information about data, and when it is very structured it can be. The importance of metadata lies in the potential for machine-to-machine interoperability, providing the user with added functionality, or 'actionable' information.<br /><br />In 2013, the term metadata took on a sinister meaning to many in the public who were disturbed by the Edward Snowden revelations about US government surveillance activity on global civilians through the telecommunications infrastructure. As it is meant in those news stories, metadata refers to the trail of data 'crumbs' you leave when you visit websites, make telephone calls or online purchases, or follow social media. According to Snowden, who had worked for a government contractor as a surveillance operative, this transactional metadata is often more revealing than the actual content of what we do online. If nothing else, these stories illustrate the potential power of metadata, regardless of how we may feel about the political decisions being made about our right to privacy or lack of it.<br /><br />]]></text><text linkID="PG1296572846140" name="Types of metadata"><![CDATA[Three broad categories of metadata are:<br /><ul><br /><li><b>Descriptive</b> - common fields such as title, author, abstract, keywords which help users to discover online sources through searching and browsing.</li><br /><li><b>Administrative</b> - preservation, rights management, and technical metadata about formats.</li><br /><li><b>Structural</b> - how different components of a set of associated data relate to one another, such as a schema describing relations between tables in a database.</li><br /></ul><br />Metadata may not be required if you are working alone on your own computer, but become crucial when data are shared online. Your data management plan should determine whether you need to apply metadata descriptors or tags at some point during your project.<br /><br />Metadata help to place your dataset in a broader context, allowing those outside your institution, discipline, or software environment to understand how to interpret your data. <br />]]></text><categories linkID="PG1311874923222" name="Match the metadata" text="Drag the metadata item to its corresponding metadata category &#x2013; there are 4 items of metadata for each category.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hint:&lt;/b&gt; You may find it helpful to use the &quot;Full Screen&quot; button in the bottom left-hand corner, and the &quot;Check Answers&quot; button in the bottom right-hand corner, which will display green ticks to highlight the correct answers." labelSize="Small"><category name="Descriptive"><item name="title"/><item name="data creator"/><item name="subject"/><item name="funder"/></category><category name="Administrative"><item name="file formats"/><item name="rights statement"/><item name="version of data"/><item undefined="" name="timestamp of transaction"/></category><category name="Structural"><item name="variable list"/><item name="database schema"/><item name="data dictionary"/><item name="taxonomy"/></category></categories><text linkID="PG1406298955268" name="The importance of data citation"><![CDATA[This section deals with a special kind of descriptive metadata, namely: data citation.<br /><br />As every scholar knows, in the course of publishing research it is essential to cite one's sources. The reference list at the end of a publication is crucial to establishing the credibility of the author's claims, as well as the provenance of a particular theory or school of thought. <br /><br />This is no less true for datasets than for publications, but somehow the practice of proper data citation has been slow to take root in academic culture. All too often we see charts in articles such as, "Source: OECD" without any further information in the reference list to help a reader look up the original data. <br /><br />Or worse, the producer of a carefully curated dataset may set in motion a number of fruitful publications by other academics without getting credit for the work that went into producing the dataset. The lack of proper recognition through citation may affect the data creator's career progression.<br /><br />Although this raises more issues than can be discussed here, a number of organisations and initiatives have attempted to rectify this by gathering evidence, publishing guidance and articles, applying pressure to bibliographic style authorities, and agreeing universal principles. <br /><br />In 2014, a group called Force 11, which believes that research data  should be treated as 'first class research objects' along with publications, issued a Joint Declaration of Data Citation Principles, which has been endorsed by a number of scientific bodies and publishers as well as individuals.<br /><a href="www.force11.org/group/joint-declaration-data-citation-principles-final" target="_blank"><br />www.force11.org/group/joint-declaration-data-citation-principles-final</a>]]></text><bleedingImage linkID="PG1402316626043" name="Why cite data?" align="Left" url="FileLocation + 'media/Folded-Map-To-Database-289.png'" tip="Courtesy of crisg http://openclipart.org/detail/182166/folded-map-by-crisg-182166" imagesize="auto"><![CDATA[“Data are a vital part of the scientific research process and proper citation should be a significant feature of research publications."<br /><br />Data citation:<br /><ul><li>acknowledges the author's sources</li><br /><li>makes identifying data easier</li><br /><li>promotes the reproduction of research results</li><br /><li>makes it easier to find data</li><br /><li>allows the impact of data to be tracked</li><br /><li>provides a structure which recognises and can reward the data creator”</li></ul><br />UK Data Service. <i>Citing data</i>. Retrieved 9 June 2014 from http://ukdataservice.ac.uk/<br /><br /><b>Why provide a data citation?</b><br />By providing a data citation for your work, you make it easier for others using your data to cite it accurately in their work.]]></bleedingImage><text linkID="PG1402307672273" name="How to cite a data source"><![CDATA[A general rule of thumb is to include enough information for the reader to locate the dataset, part of a database, or object to which the research refers. <br /><br />DataCite, an international organisation founded in London in 2009 to promote standards that help researchers find, access, and reuse data, recommends the following miminum citation elements: <br /><br />Creator (PublicationYear): Title. Publisher. Identifier<br /><br />Identifier refers to any accession number or persistent ID which uniquely identifies the object, including a DOI (digital object identifier) or even a URL (though this may be less persistent).<br /><br />Two additional properties which may be added where useful are Version and ResourceType. The latter refers to the class of object that is being cited, such as: dataset, database, table, map, sound file, image, manuscript, website, video.<br /><br />The UK Data Service recommends using a title that indicates the subject matter but also geography, and time period that the data covers.<br /><br /><b>Example:</b><br />Richardson, Elizabeth A. (2009). Carstairs deprivation scores for Scotland by CATT2, 1981, 1991, 2001 [Dataset]. University of Edinburgh. School of GeoSciences. http://hdl.handle.net/10283/19.<br /><br />Try to adopt the same style and ordering as the rest of the references. Bibliographic style guides and reference manager software may help, but inevitably some judgment may be called for. If so, err on the side of more information rather than less, to help the user find the information.<br /><br />In the case of a dynamic database that is continuously updated it may be near impossible to refer back to the exact version of the database that was originally used. In this case do include a date of download.<br /><br />In life sciences it is common to provide simply an accession number with a database name when referencing sequence data. For example: European Nucleotide Archive accession number CY115901, or NCBI SNP database accession number ss472331023 .<br /><br /><b>What if I am using an unpublished data source?</b><br />Informal data sharing is relatively common, but even if the data are unpublished, the principle still applies. If an individual gave you the data, for example in an email attachment, you can cite it as a private communication. <br /><br /><b>Example:</b><br />May, Suzanne. 2004. E-mail message. (Communications Officer, Advisory Services, Statistics Canada.) June 16.]]></text><text linkID="PG1409847775341" name="Reproducibility of Research"><![CDATA[Good practice in data documentation, metadata and data citation can all contribute to reaching a better standard of reproducibility of research. Reproducibility is a fundamental principle of the scientific method.<br /><br /><b>The three Rs</b><br />There are a lot of words that begin with R that touch on different aspects of reproducibility: repeatability, replication, reproduction, reanalysis.<br /><br />A blog post summarising an article about the 3 Rs for experimental data provided these useful distinctions:<br /><br />"1. Replication verifies that the observed findings are sufficiently stable to be discovered more than once using the same methods as the baseline experiment.<br />2. In contrast, reproduction verifies that the findings are not solely attributable to the experimental method. For this reason, a new experiment is run using different experimental methods to test the same hypotheses as the baseline experiment.<br />3. For reanalysis, the data of a previously conducted experiment are used to verify the results rather than re-running the experiment." (GBSI, 2014 - see Further reading page at end of unit).<br /><br />Victoria Stodden, an outspoken advocate of reproducible research, argues that as science becomes increasingly based on computation rather than experimentation, a credibility gap is emerging from the lack of access to the data and code needed to reproduce the results of computational science. She advocates the use of 'companion websites' for published articles that include all of the data, documentation, and code needed to reproduce the results, and helped create RunMyCode.org as an online repository allowing people to share code and data associated with scientific publications (Stodden, Hurlin and Perignon, 2012 - see 'Further reading' at the end of this unit).]]></text><gapFill linkID="PG1308558964156" name="Summary (1 of 3)" text="You have now been introduced to the concepts of documentation and metadata. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As a summary task please drag and drop the words at the bottom of the page into the gaps left in the text.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hint:&lt;/b&gt; If the word you select is not the correct word you won't be able to drop it into the gap." passage="There are many reasons why you need to document your data:&lt;br /&gt; - to |help| you remember the details later&lt;br /&gt; - to help others understand your research, verify your |findings|, |review| your submitted publication, |replicate| your results, or even |archive| your data for access and |re-use|.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Research data need to be documented at various levels:&lt;br /&gt; - |project| level&lt;br /&gt; - file or |database| level&lt;br /&gt; - and |variable| or item level. " interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="Well done! Please continue to the second part of the activity on the next screen." panelWidth="Large"/><gapFill linkID="PG1406548556570" name="Summary (2 of 3)" text="" passage="Some examples of &lt;b&gt;data documentation&lt;/b&gt; are: &lt;br /&gt; - |laboratory| notebooks&lt;br /&gt; - |methodology| reports&lt;br /&gt; - |questionnaires|&lt;br /&gt; - and software |syntax|.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Laboratory notebooks, for example, play an important role in |supporting| claims relating to intellectual property developed by University researchers, and even defending against claims of scientific |fraud|.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The term |metadata| is commonly defined as data about data. The importance of metadata lies in the potential for |machine-to-machine| interoperability, providing the user with an enhanced version of |published| data." interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="Well done! Please continue to the second part of the activity on the next screen." panelWidth="Full"/><gapFill linkID="PG1399455095216" name="Summary (3 of 3)" text="Complete these &lt;b&gt;data citations&lt;/b&gt; by dragging the correct components into the spaces." passage="Complete these &lt;b&gt;data citations&lt;/b&gt; by dragging the correct components into the spaces.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt; |Paterson, Lindsay|; O'Hanlon, Fiona. (2013). Public Attitudes to Gaelic in Scotland. Colchester, Essex: UK Data Archive.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt; Lass, Roger; Laing, Margaret; Alcorn, Rhona; Williamson, Ian K. (2013). |Corpus of Narrative Etymologies|. Edinburgh: University of Edinburgh.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt; Smith, D.J. (April 2004). Edinburgh Study of Youth Transitions and Crime: Waves One to Four, 1997-2001 [computer file]. Colchester, Essex: |UK Data Archive|. SN: 4800. http://dx.doi.org/10.5255/UKDA-SN-4800-1&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt; European Nucleotide Archive, |accession number EF158117.1 |&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;" interactivity="Drag Drop" feedback="Congratulations! You have successfully completed this unit." panelWidth="Full"/><text playNarration="false" linkID="PG1376644609653" name="Next &amp; further reading"><![CDATA[<p><b>What to do next</b>?
  <br />
  <br />
  You have now completed this unit. Take a look at &#39;Further reading&#39; where you will find a list of resources that will help you gain further understanding of what constitutes and defines documentation and metadata.
  <br />
  <br />
  You could also start a new unit and come back to check these resources later. We recommend that you continue
  <br />
  with the <a href="../storageandsecurity">Storage and security</a> unit.
  <br />
  <br />
  If you prefer, you can instead go back to the <a href="http://mantra.ed.ac.uk/">MANTRA</a> home page and choose a different unit.
  <br />
  <br />
  <br />
  <b>Further reading</b>
  <br />
  <br />
  Ball, A., Duke, M. (18 October 2012). <i>How to cite datasets and link to publications</i> [How-to guides]. Digital Curation Centre. Last updated 20 June 2012.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.dcc.ac.uk/resources/how-guides/cite-datasets" target="_blank">www.dcc.ac.uk/resources/how-guides/cite-datasets</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  Ball, J. (30 September 2013). &#39;NSA stores metadata of millions of web users for up to a year, secret files show&#39; in <i>The Guardian</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/30/nsa-americans-metadata-year-documents" target="_blank">www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/30/nsa-americans-metadata-year-documents</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  CODATA-ICSTI Task Group on Data Citation Standards and Practices (2013). &#39;Out of cite, out of mind: The current state of practice, policy, and technology for the citation of data&#39; in <i>Data Science Journal.</i> Vol. 12, p. CIDCR1-CIDCR75.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2481/dsj.OSOM13-043" target="_blank">dx.doi.org/10.2481/dsj.OSOM13-043</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  DataCite. (2009). <i>Why is it so important to cite data?</i>
  <br />
  Retrieved 31 March 2017 from <a href="https://www.datacite.org/cite-your-data.html" target="_blank">www.datacite.org/cite-your-data.html</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  Day, M. (November 2005). &#39;Metadata&#39; in <i>Curation Reference Manual</i>. Digital Curation Centre.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.dcc.ac.uk/resources/curation-reference-manual/completed-chapters/metadata" target="_blank">www.dcc.ac.uk/resources/curation-reference-manual/completed-chapters/metadata</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  GBSI [Global Biological Standards Institute]. (14 January 2014). &quot;Reproducibility, Replication, and Reanalysis (Oh My).&quot; <i>The Standard Buzz Blog.</i>
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://gbsi.org/blog/2014/01/reproducibility-replication-reanalysis-oh-my">http://gbsi.org/blog/2014/01/reproducibility-replication-reanalysis-oh-my</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  Guenther, R., Radebaugh, J. (2004). <i>Understanding metadata</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://www.niso.org/publications/press/UnderstandingMetadata.pdf" target="_blank">www.niso.org/publications/press/UnderstandingMetadata.pdf</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  researchspace (8 March 2017). <i>Overview of RSpace for researchers</i> [Video file].
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4jTCdNTsW8I" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4jTCdNTsW8I</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  Stodden, V., Hurlin, C. and C. Perignon. (15 September 2012). &quot;RunMyCode.Org: A Novel Dissemination and Collaboration Platform for Executing Published Computational Results.&quot; <i>Social Science Research Network</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved from <a href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=2147710" target="_blank">http://ssrn.com/abstract=2147710</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  UK Data Archive (UKDA). <i>Create and manage data: documenting your data</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved 4 August 2014 from <a href="http://www.data-archive.ac.uk/create-manage/document" target="_blank">www.data-archive.ac.uk/create-manage/document</a>
  <br />
  <br />
  UK Data Service. <i>Citing data</i>.
  <br />
  Retrieved 4 August 2014 from <a href="http://ukdataservice.ac.uk/use-data/citing-data.aspx" target="_blank">ukdataservice.ac.uk/use-data/citing-data.aspx</a>
</p>
]]></text></learningObject>
